<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reviler rebuked, or, Abraham Bonifield's envy, falseness and folly, in his late book, called The cry of the oppressed, etc., laid open in this answer thereunto Written by Oliver Sansom...</title>
            <author>Sansom, Oliver, 1636-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476322</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94202)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2254:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reviler rebuked, or, Abraham Bonifield's envy, falseness and folly, in his late book, called The cry of the oppressed, etc., laid open in this answer thereunto Written by Oliver Sansom...</title>
                  <author>Sansom, Oliver, 1636-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata : p. 46.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, faded print.</note>
                  <note>Includes, bound at end, t.p. only, of: Ashby, R. The folly of a libeller made manifest.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Durham Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bonifield, Abraham, fl. 1692-1694. --  Cry of the oppressed.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151315:1"/>
            <p>A Reviler Rebuked: OR, <hi>Abraham Bonifield's</hi> ENVY, FALSENESS and FOLLY, In his Late Book, Called, <hi>The CRY of the OPPRESSED, &amp;c.</hi> LAID OPEN In this ANSWER thereunto.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>OLIVER SANSOM.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Behold he Travelleth with Iniquity, and hath Conceived Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and brought forth Falſhood. He made a Pit and digged it, and is fallen into the Ditch which he hath made. His Miſchief ſhall return upon his own Head, and his violent Dealing ſhall come down upon his own Pate,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 7.14. 15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> near the <hi>Meeting Houſe</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151315:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151315:3"/>
            <head>A REVILER REBUKED; OR, <hi>Abraham Bonifield's</hi> ENVY, FALSNESS and FOLLY in his late Book, called the <hi>Cry of the Oppreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. laid open in this Anſwer thereunto.</head>
            <p>OF the many ways which Satan hath uſed to caſt reproach upon the Way of Truth, and them that truly walk therein, thereby to hinder thoſe that are enquiring after it, from entering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into: One (and that not the leaſt miſchievous) hath been to ſtir up Diſcontent, Emulation, or Envy in ſome or other, who make, or have made Profeſſion of the ſame Way of Truth, againſt either ſome particular Member, or the whole Society; and having drawn them by degrees into Prejudice and Enmity, then to thruſt them forward, to make open War by Word or Writing, and to load the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Profeſſors of Truth with Calumny, Reproach and falſe Accuſations. How much the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered by ſuch, either Falſe Pretenders to, or Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders and Apoſtates from the Way of Truth, may be gathered from divers occaſional hints, in many of his Epiſtles. There were ſome <hi>High Talkers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that were <hi>puffed up againſt the Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.18, 19. Some that were ready to <hi>Cenſure him</hi> as if he <hi>walked according to the Fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.2. Some who <hi>deſpiſed his Bodily preſence, as weak,</hi> and counted his <hi>Speech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible,</hi> ver. 10. Such he called <hi>Falſe Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Deceitful Workers,</hi> cap. 11:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151315:4"/>ver. 13. And recounting the many Sufferings, Hardſhips and Perils he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone for the ſake of the Goſpel, mentions his <hi>Perils among falſe Brethren,</hi> ver. 26. He complains to the <hi>Galatians</hi> of <hi>falſe Brethren</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem, who ſought to bring him into Bondage,</hi> Gal. 2.4. He tells the <hi>Philippians, That ſome at</hi> Rome <hi>Preached Chriſt even of Envy, Strife and Contention, not ſincerely, ſuppoſing to add affliction to his Bonds,</hi> Phil. 1.15, 16. He warns <hi>Timothy</hi> of <hi>Alexander the Copper-ſmith, who,</hi> (he ſays) <hi>did him much evil, and greatly withſtood his Preaching,</hi> 2. Tim. 4.14, 15. Nor was the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> free from the like Exerciſe and Suffering from <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes,</hi> who <hi>prated againſt him with malicious words,</hi> 3 John 9, 10. So that it need not ſeem ſtrange to any now, neither ſhould any be ſtartled at it, to ſee ſome riſe up amongſt us, or pretending to be of us, and fall upon us with bitter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings and falſe Accuſations; ſince it appears to have been the work of the wicked One, in former Ages, to ſtir up ſuch perverſe and unruly Spirits, to Rail at, Revile, Reproach and Defame even the Apoſtles themſelves. Which evil work he hath continued ever ſince; and in this Age eſpecially, wherein the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath broken forth more brightly and clearly, than in many Ages before; he hath drawn ſome that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to walk therein, into <hi>Diſcontent, Diviſion, Prejudice, Enmity,</hi> and ſo at length into <hi>open Oppoſition,</hi> even to Write, Print and publiſh Books ſtuffed with <hi>Falſhoods</hi> and <hi>Defamations</hi> againſt the Faithful Followers and Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Among the too many whom Satan hath beguiled, corrupted and hardened to that degree, <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> of <hi>Reading</hi> is one, who having long ſince diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himſelf to be a Man of a <hi>reſtleſs and unquiet Mind,</hi> and of an unruly and contentious Spirit, ſeeking occaſions to make Diſturbances, and break the Peace of the Church, was divers years ago reproved therefore, and teſtified againſt, by the <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> of the County <hi>where he lives.</hi> And having ſince left the Meeting of Friends (to which he us'd before to reſort) and joyned himſelf to them in <hi>Reading,</hi> who, ſome years ago, Separated themſelves from Friends; he hath very lately Publiſhed a Book in Print, containing many <hi>Foul Reflections, Slanderous Reports,</hi> and <hi>Falſe Accuſations</hi> againſt divers Friends by Name, among whom he hath made me a principal <hi>Butt,</hi> to ſhoot his <hi>Envious Arrows</hi> at, and hath laboured much to defame me in my Reputation, both as a Man and a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; I find a concern upon my Spirit, to Vindicate Truth, and other Friends concerned, as well as my ſelf, from his <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Foul Aſperſions,</hi> and to lay open his Deceit and Wickedneſs therein.</p>
            <p>He calls his Book, <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed in Sion:</hi> But by the <hi>Confuſion</hi> that is in it, he manifeſts himſelf to be in <hi>Babylon;</hi> He ſhould have told what he means by <hi>Sion.</hi> For as <hi>Sion</hi> outwardly was a Mountain in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> upon, or near which the <hi>Temple</hi> was ſaid to be builded: So <hi>Sion</hi> Spiritually, or in a Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Senſe, is uſed for that Holy Mountain, which the Prophet ſpoke of, when deſcribing the Peace of Chriſt's Kingdom in the Goſpel-Days, he ſaid, <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain,</hi> Iſa. 11.9. And to ſuch as come to dwell in this Holy Mountain, the ſame Prophet ſaid elſewhere, <hi>In Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed; Thou ſhalt be far from Oppreſſion, for thou ſhalt not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151315:4"/>fear; and from terrour, for it ſhall not come near thee,</hi> Chap. 54.14. Whence then has he fetched his <hi>Cry of the Oppreſſed in Sion?</hi> He ſays, it is <hi>Sounded forth aloud in the Camp:</hi> But he doth not ſay what Camp. Surely it muſt be in the Camp of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumcifed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides his <hi>Cry,</hi> he hath given another Title to his Book, he calls it alſo, <hi>An Appeal from the Wicked and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Judgment of Men, to the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that Juſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Judge and Lord of Heaven and Earth; And to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Witneſs in the Hearts and inward parts of all the Real Profeſſors and Poſſeſſors of the Holy Truth.</hi> Here he makes a two-fold Appeal, one to the <hi>Judgment-Seat of Chriſt,</hi> another to his <hi>Holy Witneſs in the Hearts,</hi> &amp;c. by diſtinguiſhing of which, it ſeems as if he referred in the former, to the general Judgment at the end of the World. For that world <hi>[Judgment-Seat]</hi> is uſed in that Senſe by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> chap. 14. ver. 10. <hi>For we ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt;</hi> and 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we muſt all appear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that he hath done, whether good or bad.</hi> And I do not remember it is uſed in any other Senſe in Scripture, unleſs it be with Relation to Civil Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Beſides theſe, he hath yet a <hi>Third</hi> and more particular Appeal in his Book, <hi>page</hi> 30. where he <hi>Appeals to all that have Eyes of their own, and dare uſe them.</hi> I am well content to <hi>joyn Iſſue</hi> with him upon all his <hi>Three Appeals,</hi> and to abide the Judgment, both of <hi>God's Witneſs</hi> in the Hearts of his People at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and of Chriſt himſelf hereafter at the great day; nor do I fear the Cenſure of any, who have Eyes of their own, and dare and will uſe them <hi>aright.</hi> And had not <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> called his Book, <hi>A True and Impartial Account of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Forcing, Severe Ways, Arbitrary and Indirect Methods,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhould not perhaps have ſo much regarded his Perſonal Reflections upon my ſelf (though they are very <hi>Foul</hi> and <hi>Falſe</hi>) as to have beſtowed an Anſwer on him. But for the Honour of Truth, and clearing of other Friends concerned therein, as well as my ſelf, and to prevent his Deceiving and Miſleading any who do not ſo well know him, I think fit to lay open and unravel his Spiders Web (which is his own Phraſe <hi>p.</hi> 26) not doubting to manifeſt to the indifferent Reader, that his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (which he calls True and Impartial) is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntrue</hi> and <hi>Partial;</hi> that his <hi>Cry of Oppreſſion by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Forcing, Severe Ways,</hi> &amp;c. is as <hi>Cauſeleſs,</hi> as he is <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous,</hi> and that he hath <hi>knowingly</hi> wronged me in thoſe <hi>Wicked Reports</hi> he hath Publiſhed concerning me. Yet before I enter upon his Book it ſelf, his Epiſtle to the Reader lying in my way, and being ſo <hi>bulky</hi> as to take up <hi>ten pages,</hi> it may be thought much, if I ſhould wholly paſs over it, without taking any notice of it. Some few Obſervations therefore I think fit to make, on ſome few Paſſages in it.</p>
            <p>He begins with as much <hi>Smoothneſs</hi> as he can, to inſinuate himſelf into his Reader, pretending much to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Plainneſs;</hi> but he cannot hold to that long. He quickly falls into <hi>Heat, Anger, Railing</hi> and bitter Language, and in that heat runs into a ſort of Prophetick Strain, denouncing Judgments againſt others; and undertaking, after his manner, to foretel what ſhall befal them, whom he calls <hi>Proud and Haughty Minded.</hi> But galloping on too faſt without
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151315:5"/>true Senſe, or due Coſinderation, he Stumbles, Falls and Foyls himſelf moſt ſhamefully; for ſpeaking of thoſe whom he calls <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Haughty Minded,</hi> he ſays, <hi>They have digreſſed from the Truth, and too far played the Harlot thereby with the Lord, the ancient Rock of their Salvation.</hi> Did ever any Man of ſober Senſe drop ſuch an Expreſſion as this? The Prophets of God did often reprove back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, for going a Whoring <hi>from God,</hi> Hoſea, 4.12. and chap. 9.1. And playing the Harlot <hi>with</hi> others. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.28. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.1. But whoever heard before of playing the Harlot <hi>with</hi> the Lord? By this the Reader may taſte and ſee how far <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> is Digreſſed, or gone aſide from Truth, and what Spirit guided him in Writing his Book, which hath led him to uſe ſuch a groſs and unſound Expreſſion. This is in the 5th <hi>page</hi> of his <hi>Epiſtle:</hi> And in the ſame he gives his Reader to underſtand (whereby the Reader may ſee and obſerve what a <hi>Quarrelſome Man</hi> he has been) that this is not <hi>the firſt Difference, no, not by ſeveral,</hi> that he has been concerned in with Friends in that Town of <hi>Reading.</hi> And as if he Gloried in this (which he might rather be aſhamed of) he divides them into <hi>Small or Pettyones, and more General,</hi> or <hi>moſt Capital ones.</hi> It ſeems <hi>Small</hi> or <hi>Petty</hi> matters will ſerve for a ground or occaſion of difference with ſuch a <hi>Pettiſh</hi> Spirit as he is of. But he need not boaſt of that: For it is not for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And indeed, if he had had any real regard for the Honour of Truth, and the Reputation of that Chriſtian Society, which he once profeſſed himſelf a Member of, and is now <hi>without juſt cauſe</hi> become an Enemy to, it would have reſtrained him from Publiſhing Differences long ſince paſt and gone, eſpecially wherein he himſelf was ſo deeply concerned, and thereby to expoſe both the one and the other to the Scorn and Contempt of ſuch prophane Readers as his Book may go amongſt. But he muſt gratifie his Envy, though he wound himſelf in endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to wound others. Three Differences therefore he here ſets forth, which he calls more General, or moſt Capital ones. The <hi>firſt</hi> he ſays, <hi>was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to be heard and ended by</hi> Jo. Oſgood <hi>and</hi> John Kilborne, <hi>wherein ſeveral others,</hi> he ſays, <hi>were likewiſe concerned, as well as himſelf.</hi> Thoſe words <hi>[ſeveral others]</hi> are a common Shelter for him to hide himſelf under, when he would make his Reader believe that other Friends took part with him in his Quarrels, but how falſe he is in that I ſhall ſhew anon, when I come to Examine his Book it ſelf. What that Difference was about, he has not told his Reader. Generals ſerve <hi>Slanderers</hi> beſt to lurk under. In general therefore he ſays, <hi>Several Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were drawn up, ſtated and given againſt</hi> W. L. <hi>and were moſt of them ſuch too,</hi> ſays he, <hi>as I think, ſearce ever the like in the Nature and Degree of them, as with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to</hi> W. L. <hi>his Arrogance and Pride, hath at any time come before Friends ſince they were a People.</hi> Is not this ſet out at an high rate? From this general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, what could the Reader conceive; but that <hi>W. L.</hi> was the height of Pride and Arrogance? Whereas they that know him, know him to be no ſuch Man; and it's more applicable unto <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> himſelf. 'Tis true, he had drawn up many Charges, and written many Scandalous Papers againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> tending to defame him: But when the matters came to be looked into and examined, the Friends to whom it was referred, did not judge <hi>W. L.</hi> to be guilty of that which <hi>A. B.</hi> had charged him with. But <hi>A. B.</hi> thereupon burned his own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151315:5"/>Papers himſelf that ſame Evening at <hi>John Buys</hi> Kiln-fire; and whether this was not a Teſtimony againſt what he had written, let the Reader judge: And was it not then agreed, that whoever revived the ſaid Difference again, ſhould be deemed the offending Perſon? He goes on ſaying, <hi>And the Remarks of the aforeſaid made upon both his Charges, Perſon, Qualifications,</hi> W. L. <hi>may happily ſtill remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Whom does he mean by <hi>[the aforeſaid?]</hi> He muſt mean either <hi>J. O.</hi> and <hi>J. K.</hi> (to whom, he ſays, <hi>the Difference was referred</hi>) or himſelf, and his <hi>[ſeveral others]</hi> who he ſays were concerned in it as well as himſelf. If he means thoſe two Friends (<hi>J. O.</hi> and <hi>J. K.</hi>) <hi>W. L.</hi> doth not at all remember that they made any Remarks upon his Charges, Perſon, or Qualifications. And he believes they were Honeſter and Wiſer Men, than to make Remarks upon his Perſon or Qualifications. But if by <hi>[the aforeſaid]</hi> he means himſelf and his pretended <hi>(ſeveral others)</hi> concerned with him, it ſhews what <hi>Cavilling Spirits</hi> he and they were of, and what <hi>Quarrelſome Qualifications</hi> they had, that would go to make Remarks upon <hi>W. L</hi>'s Perſon and Qualifications. What Perſons or Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>A. B</hi>'s <hi>(ſeveral others)</hi> were of, I know not; but <hi>A. B.</hi> I think, might very well have let <hi>W. L</hi>'s Perſon and Qualifications alone. And notwithſtanding the <hi>big</hi> Words and <hi>empty</hi> Flouriſhes, which <hi>A. B.</hi> hath uſed to ſet forth the greatneſs of the <hi>Capital</hi> Difference, as he calls it; it ſeems the Difference was but ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> if it wanted to be made out by Remarks upon his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Qualifications.</hi> But be that Difference what it would, ſince <hi>A. B.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges it was not only referred to be heard and ended by <hi>J. O.</hi> and <hi>J. K.</hi> but alſo that it was ſo: (for he adds; <hi>as accordingly they were,</hi> viz. heard and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) who but one of a reſtleſs and unquiet Mind, an Evil Contentious Spirit, would have renewed the remembrance of an old <hi>ended</hi> Difference? By this the Reader may ſee ſome of <hi>A. Bonifield</hi>'s Qualifications, and by theſe gueſs at the reſt, which are ſo <hi>Remarkably Evil,</hi> that they need no farther <hi>Remark</hi> to be made upon them.</p>
            <p>In the 8th <hi>page</hi> of his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> he reflects not only on <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> but on the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings too. For having ſet forth (but very falſly) the great Endeavours and Entreaties he uſed to obtain Juſtice and a fair Hearing (as he pretended) he adds, <hi>Tho' all in vain and to no purpoſe, becauſe of their ſo over-ſwaying of Meetings for Affection and Intereſt; becauſe ſtill and always</hi> (ſays he) <hi>There was a Ruling Party both in Monthly and Quarterly Meetings; ſo that what they were minded or reſolved ſhould be, was to be; and what not, neither could, ſhould, nor was to be admitted.</hi> That this is a great Falſhood and Slander upon the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings of our County of <hi>Berks,</hi> is notoriouſly known to all our Friends that frequent thoſe Meetings, and therefore need no other Refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there being ſo many that can Witneſs againſt it: But it is uſual with him to charge his own Faults upon others; and <hi>Preheminence</hi> being the thing he hath long aimed at, and ſought after, that he might <hi>Sway, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Over-rule</hi> Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at his pleaſure; his being diſappointed thereof (by them he mentions, and other Friends alſo, who ſaw his Ambitious, Aſpiring Humour, and Contentious Temper, and oppoſed him therein) hath ſtirred up in him a Spirit of Revenge, to upbraid them with that which himſelf was guilty of. But as herein he hath done
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151315:6"/>wickedly, ſo hath he alſo done it fooliſhly, and the Reward of Fools, Confuſion and Self-contradiction, falls upon him. For when he hath charged <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> with over-ſwaying Meetings for Affection and Intereſt; ſo that what they were minded or reſolved ſhould be, was to be; and what they were minded ſhould not be, neither could, ſhould, nor was to be admitted: He immediately adds, <hi>And it may be alſo obſerved, how doubtful and timerous</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. <hi>&amp;c. all along from firſt to laſt, have been of themſelves, and concerning the Effect and Event of things.</hi> Was this a ſign of their having, or being of a <hi>Ruling</hi> Party in Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Quarterly Meetings? If they had ſo <hi>over ſwayed</hi> Meetings, as he ſays, that what they were minded ſhould be, was to be; and what they were minded ſhould not be, neither could, ſhould, nor was to be admitted, ſurely they needed not to have been doubtful and timerous (as he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them) concerning the Effect and Event of Things. Here <hi>A. Bonifield</hi>'s Paſſion hath run him on ground. He deſigned to <hi>defame</hi> thoſe Friends <hi>at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and the firſt thing he charges them with, is <hi>Superiority, Rule, Sway</hi> in and over Meetings, both Monthly and Quarterly, ſo that <hi>they could do what they pleaſed;</hi> what they had a mind to have done, muſt be done; and what they would not have done, muſt not be done, ſays he. This, if it were true, were bad enough, one would think, and he needed not have heaped up more. But his Envy extended further. Therefore running on without Conſideration, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents them at the ſame time, <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>timerous,</hi> not conſidering how diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable thoſe terms are, to that great ſtrength and power of Sway and Rule, which he had but juſt before repreſented them to have in and over Meetings, by which they could do, or keep undone, whatſoever they pleaſed. The truth is, both the one and the other is a Falſhood, and a Slander of his own deviſing; and this diſcovery of his Folly is very juſt upon him.</p>
            <p>Now that himſelf was guilty of ſeeking and endeavouring to carry on his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious Deſign by Intereſt, he himſelf has (unadviſedly) acknowledged in this place. For ſpeaking of an Appeal, which he falſly ſays was pretendedly ſought, endeavoured and allowed by <hi>O. S.</hi> he adds, <hi>And earneſtly and truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by me, and that by all the thought-of ways, means and intereſt that poſſibly I could find, obtain, or make uſe of, on my part, in order thereunto.</hi> So that though there was no cauſe for the Appeal he mentions, nor ground for him to charge me (as he doth here, and frequently in his Book) with ſeeking, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and allowing it (to which I may anſwer in its place) yet he plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers that that which he wrongfully blames thoſe Friends for, to wit, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaying of Meetings for Affection and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> was the courſe he took for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on his Appeal, namely, by all the thought-of ways, means, and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> that poſſibly he could find, obtain, or make uſe of on his part, as his own words are.</p>
            <p>Beſides the former, he contradicts himſelf again in this place. For ſpeaking of his Intreaties, uſed ſtill, and all along from time to time, and one time to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for but Juſtice and a fair Hearing in his Caſe, he adds, <hi>in both this and the former Differences:</hi> And he confeſt but a little before, p. 5. that one of the two former Differences was heard and ended by <hi>J. O.</hi> and <hi>J. K.</hi> and in this place acknowledges the two former were heard and ended: So that there is <hi>no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151315:6"/>end of Contention with him,</hi> but rather than be quiet, he will call for Juſtice, and a fair Hearing, even of ſuch Differences as himſelf acknowledges have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, heard and ended before.</p>
            <p>More Obſervations might be made on his Epiſtle; but theſe foregoing may ſomewhat diſcover what Spirit and Temper he is of, which the Book it ſelf will afford occaſions of manifeſting more fully. I ſhall therefore here only note, that he flatters with his Reader at the end of his Epiſtle, as he did at the beginning of it, and after he hath vented a great deal of <hi>Bitterneſs, Envy,</hi> and <hi>Falſhood</hi> in it, ſubſcribes himſelf in the cloſe thereof, <hi>Thine in the Truth that is plain, innocent, and void of the beguiling Crafts of Men.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, that Truth is plain and innocent, and void of the beguiling Crafts of Men; But it is alſo true, That he is not in that Truth, but out of it, and contending againſt them that dwell in it: And his pretending to be in the Truth that is void of the Beguiling Crafts of Men, is but a <hi>Crafty Artifice</hi> of his, to beguile his Reader by.</p>
            <p>To his Epiſtle he tacks on ſomething, by way of Introduction to his Book, in which he opens (perhaps unawares) the Ground of the preſent Difference, <hi>viz.</hi> That after the former Difference had been <hi>ended,</hi> he and ſome others <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected ſome omiſſion or ſhortneſs</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in our not ſo ſtating it in the former, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to that part of the Difference, we thought very material and neceſſary to have been inſerted, as the Ground or Hinge upon which moſt of our Diſcontents did hang and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, upon which occaſion</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the old matter not brought before to light, and more new ones daily appearing, did occaſion me to draw up firſt my own particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactions, in order to preſent, and to have them heard and redreſſed either by the Monthly or Quarterly Meetings. And therefore</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in order thereunto, I preſented the Monthly Meeting with a Paper of Complaint of my Aggrievances.</hi> See now Reader, the <hi>reſtleſs</hi> Temper of this <hi>Contentious</hi> Man, that no ſooner was one Difference with him <hi>ended,</hi> but he began to <hi>ſtudy</hi> how to <hi>raiſe</hi> another. He <hi>feigns</hi> ſome freſh occaſion, and thereupon pretends to recollect ſome omiſſion or ſhortneſs in ſtating the for mer Difference, that he might take <hi>freſh</hi> occaſion to <hi>differ again.</hi> But is it not ſtrange, that this pretended omiſſion ſhould be of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing relating to that part of the Difference, which he and his thought <hi>very mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> and neceſſary to have been inſerted, as the <hi>Ground</hi> or <hi>Hinge</hi> upon which moſt of their Diſcontents (he ſays) did hang and depend? This was a ſhortneſs indeed, ſufficient to <hi>unhinge</hi> all their Diſcontents, and render the Difference, at leaſt on their ſide, <hi>gronndleſs.</hi> But rather than his Diſcontents ſhould want an <hi>Hinge</hi> ſtill to turn and return upon, he would bring forth old matter not brought to light before, for he ſays, <hi>upon which occaſion, the old matter not brought before to light, and more new ones daily appearing, did occaſion me to draw up firſt my own particular Diſſatisfactions.</hi> Was this like the Truth that is <hi>plain and innocent, and void of the beguiling Crafts of Men?</hi> Doth not this either diſcover the <hi>beguiling Craft or Folly of a Man out of Truth, and neither plain nor innocent,</hi> thus to keep back ſome old matter, (and that too no leſs, it ſeems, than the Ground or Hinge upon which, he ſays, moſt of their Diſcontents did hang and depend) and not inſert it, not bring it to light, when his old Difference was to be put an end to?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151315:7"/>
            <p>Now having drawn up his own particular Diſſatisfactions, <hi>I preſented the Monthly Meeting,</hi> ſays he, <hi>with a Paper of Complaint of my Aggrievances.</hi> This Paper of Complaint one might reaſonably expect ſhould have been the firſt in his Book; but it is not brought forth till in his 7th page. But his Book begins with another Paper, pretended to be a Complaint of ſeveral Friends belonging to the Monthly Meeting of <hi>Reading,</hi> to the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Ore,</hi> againſt <hi>W. Lambell,</hi> for not Recording in the Monthly Meeting-Book <hi>A. Bonifield</hi>'s particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Complaint againſt him and <hi>Jo. Buy.</hi> Now though his Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.r</hi> were in order of time before his Complaint to the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Ore,</hi> againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> yet ſince he hath placed the latter firſt, I will give ſome account of that firſt. It is a Complaint againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> conſiſting of two parts, one for refuſing to Record in the Monthly Meeting-Book the Complaint he had made to that Meeting againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>John Buy;</hi> and that Meeting's referring it to the Quarterly Meeting; the other, for not bringing the Meeting's Book to the Meeting, and refuſing to let him have it to look into. The better to ſet off his Complaint, and to give the more Countenance and Authority to it, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that <hi>ſeveral other Friends, belonging to the Meeting, were troubled and ſore grieved at</hi> W. L's refuſing to Record his Complaint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>did from thence take occaſion to draw up that Paper of Complaint to the Quarterly Meeting againſt him,</hi> and that thoſe Friends did <hi>appoint him</hi> (A. B.) <hi>to deliver it on their behalf, as alſo on his own;</hi> and accordingly he hath ſigned the Paper thus, [<hi>By</hi> Abraham Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, <hi>on the behalf of the reſt concerned</hi>]. Now in all this he hath not acted in the <hi>Truth that is plain and innocent,</hi> but hath uſed <hi>beguiling Craft</hi> to deceive his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For when the Friends, appointed by the Quarterly Meeting to hear his Complaint, and end the Difference, came to examine the Matter, and inquire into the Particulars, I well remember, (for I was one of them) that when we asked him who, and what Friends of <hi>Reading</hi> Meeting were one with him in that Complaint, which he had ſigned on the behalf of the reſt concerned, he could not, or would not, name one, but <hi>R. Sandilands</hi> being preſent, did acknowledge that he was one with <hi>A. B.</hi> therein. And whereas he Charges <hi>W. L.</hi> (and it is the main part of his Charge) that he refuſed to Record the Complaint in the Monthly Meeting-Book (after the Meeting had referred it to the Quarterly Meeting) notwithſtanding that it was the Order, Concluſion and Agreement of the Monthly Meeting. I do not remember that it was made appear to us that the Monthly Meeting did order <hi>W. L.</hi> to Record it in their Book, though they did refer it to the Quarterly Meeting to end it. And it doth appear by the Coom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint it ſelf, as <hi>A. B.</hi> has publiſhed it, that <hi>W. L.</hi> did not refuſe to ſtande to the Agreement of the Monthly Meeting, for referring it to the Quarterly Meeting to be ended. For the Complaint ſaith, <hi>The Meeting came to this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> viz. <hi>to refer it to the Quarterly Meeting to end, to which both Parties did agree.</hi> So that the ſubſtance of the Matter was anſwered by <hi>W. L.</hi> in agreeing with the Monthly Meeting to refer it to the Quarterly Meeting. And it is no ſign that the Monthly Meeting was offended with <hi>W. L.</hi> for not Recording it; that moſt of the Friends belonging to that Meeting, when they underſtood <hi>A. B</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to Complain of <hi>W. L.</hi> at the Quarterly Meeting, did ſign a Certificate
<pb facs="tcp:151315:7"/>on behalf of <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> of which this following is a Copy, directed thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Ore,</hi>
                     <date>the 15th of the 7th Month, 1690.</date>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <q>WHereas our Friend <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> has taken Offence in his Mind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Dear Friends <hi>John Buy</hi> and <hi>William Lambole,</hi> more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and in this offenſive Mind hath been raking diſlikes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> both to the Diſquieting of himſelf, and alſo to the Grief and Sorrow of Friends. Now theſe may let you know, that we whoſe Names are here under-written, being Eye and Ear-witneſſes of the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and their Deportment amongſt us, do give you to underſtand our Senſe concerning them, which is, They are Men fearing God, and of a Clean Converſation, and make Conſcience in the ſight of God of what their Practice is. And whereas our Friend <hi>A. B.</hi> has let into his Mind that <hi>W. L.</hi> doth exerciſe Lordſhip over his Brethren, and ſet himſelf in Judgment over Honeſt Friends; and many things of this kind and nature: As for our parts, we ſee no ſuch Practice or Spirit appear in either <hi>J. B.</hi> or <hi>W. L.</hi> This we thought fit to ſignifie to you, in the behalf of the Bleſſed Truth, and our Antient Friends; with the Salutation of our Dear Love in the Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Truth, remain your Friends.</q>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>This was Signed by <hi>William Speakman,</hi> and 20 Friends more.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This was not Read at that ſaid Meeting, becauſe <hi>A. B</hi>'s Complaint was not openly Read, but at another Quarterly Meeting afterwards it was Read.</p>
            <p>But now it is worth the Reader's noting (in order to have a better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of <hi>A. B.</hi>) how falſly he (who pretends to be <hi>in the Truth that is plain and innocent, and void of the beguiling Crafts of Men</hi>) dealt with the Monthly Meeting in this Caſe. He had Exhibited to the Monthly Meeting a Paper of Charges, by way of Complaint, againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and he acknowledges he had the liberty granted him to Read the ſame in the Meeting. The Meeting alſo, he ſays, Unanimouſly concluded to refer it to the Quarterly Meeting to end it. And to this Reference both Parties, <hi>viz. A. B.</hi> himſelf, as well as <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> did agree. Obſerve now how well he proſecuted his Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> before the Quarterly Meeting, for he never carried it thither at all, (which was his part to have done) he confeſſes ſo himſelf in his 3d page thus, <hi>It is to be obſerved</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that it was only the foregoing Paper of Complaint, containing the Grievances of ſeveral Friends belonging to the Monthly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at</hi> Reading, <hi>that was delivered by me to the Quarterly. Meeting at Ore, the</hi> 7th <hi>Month,</hi> 1690. <hi>but not one jot or tittle in particular as from my ſelf, or concerning, or
<pb facs="tcp:151315:8"/>relating to the ſever as Articles I had in Charge againſt</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. But he let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that drop, frames a <hi>new</hi> Complaint only againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> pretending as if ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Friends were concerned in it, and that he ſigned it on their Behalf, (though we could find none to own it but <hi>R. S.</hi> and himſelf.)</p>
            <p>But to proceed; On the 15th of the 7th Month, 1690. <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>new</hi> Complaint to the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Ore;</hi> which the Meeting took, but underſtanding it to be but a private Paper, not coming from the Monthly Meeting, nor the ſame that was by the Monthly Meeting's Conſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred thither, did not think fit to trouble the whole Quarterly Meeting with private Quarrels, or particular Jangles; but committed it to Eight Friends of the Meeting, whom the Meeting nominated, and choſe to hear, and determine that, and all other Differences between <hi>A. B.</hi> (or any others that joined with him) and <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> And when the Meeting had concluded on this way, <hi>A. B.</hi> was called in, and the Agreement of the Meeting Read to him, with the Names of the Eight Friends to whom it was referred. He excepted againſt one of them, who was therepon left out, and the Matter left to the other Seven, with which A. B. ſeemed ſatisfied and contented, asking the Meeting, whether it was intended that thoſe Seven Friends ſhould hear and end only the Matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that Complaint, or all other Differences depending between <hi>W. L. J. B.</hi> and him? To which the Meeting anſwered, that thoſe Seven Friends were appointed to hear and end all Differences whatſoever between him, <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and others concerned therein. He was very deſirous to have had his Complaint Read in the open Meeting. But the Meeting for divers Reaſons did not think it proper.</p>
            <p>Of the Seven Friends, to whom this Service was by the Quarterly Meeting committed, I was one. And though A. <hi>Bonifield</hi> is ſo violently ſet, and inveighs ſo bitterly againſt me now, I ſuppoſe I ſtood fairer in his Opinion then; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he having the liberty of Exception allowed him, and making uſe of it (as he did) to exclude one, he might have alſo excepted againſt me, and thereby have faved me a great deal of trouble, and himſelf the pains of railing at me as he hath ſince done: However we undertook this Service (I can truly ſay for my ſelf, and believe I may ſafely ſay it for the reſt of my Friends concerned) with a Conſciencious regard to the Honour of God, the Proſperity of Truth, and the Peace of the Church in that Place. And accordingly, on the 23d day of the ſame 7th Month, 1690. we met at <hi>Reading,</hi> and being gathered together, waiting on the Lord, in a weighty Senſe of his Living Power and Preſence with us, after ſome time we deſired <hi>A. B.</hi> (who was preſent among us) to bring forth what he had to offer to our Conſideration; whereupon he ſtood up, and made a Speech, telling us he was diſſatisfied with the proceedings of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting, becauſe they refuſed to let him read his Paper openly in the Meeting. And inſtead of giving us his Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> he Read to us a Writing, containing ſomething which he called Reaſons why he refuſed to bring his Cauſe before us; in which he reflected foully on the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting's Proceedings, as Unjuſt, Uncharitable, and Immoral; and ſaid, he would Appeal to the next Yearly Meeting, where he hoped to have more Juſt
<pb facs="tcp:151315:8"/>and Impartial Proceedings to Redreſs his Grievances. We earneſtly deſired, and laboured to perſwade him to bring forth his Grievances before us (that if there were any Cauſe, we might Redreſs them) according to the Order of the Quarterly Meeting, to which himſelf had agreed; but all that we could ſay to him, did not at all prevail with him, to give up the Matter in queſtion, or Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to be heard by us. Yet at length he did bring forth that Paper of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> which he had before offered to the Quarterly Meeting, and Read it to us; but when he had done, he would neither refer the Matters therein complained of to us, nor let us have the Paper of Complaint. See now, Reader, the <hi>crooked ſteps</hi> he made in this Buſineſs thus far. Firſt, he brought a Paper of Charges to the Monthly Meeting againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and got that referred to the Quarterly Meeting. When the Quarterly Meeting came, where it behoved him to have made good thoſe Charges, he let them quite drop, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver proſecuted them at all there, (though referred thither by his own conſent) but inſtead of them, exhibits a <hi>new</hi> Complaint at the Quarterly Meeting againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> This, together with the former, the Quarterly Meeting referred to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Friends to hear and end, and to this he conſented, at leaſt (as himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes) condeſcended; when theſe Seven met, as above, about it, he had found a new <hi>ſtarting-hole</hi> to ſlip out at, and inſtead of proſecuting his Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> referred from the Monthly Meeting, or his Complaint againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> only, exhibited by himſelf at the Quarterly Meeting, he lets them both fall, <hi>picks a new quarrel</hi> with the Quarterly Meeting, for not letting him Read his Complaint in the open Meeting, and thereupon refuſes tryal, and nothing will ſerve him but to Appeal to the Yearly Meeting. Judge now, Reader, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Man ſeeks Peace or no, and ſtudies to be quiet; or whether he does not rather bend all his Wits and Force to create and continue Contention and Strife, that <hi>no end</hi> may be put to Differences.</p>
            <p>When we ſaw he was obſtinately bent to anſwer his own Will, and would not be perſwaded to yield to Truth and Reaſon, we told him to this effect, <hi>That we held our ſelves obliged for Truth ſake, and in diſcharge of that Truſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us by the Quarterly Meeting, to do what we could to ſtop the further ſpreading of thoſe Contentions among them, and ſhould endeavour to find out, by enquiry amongſt the Friends of the Town, the true ſtate of the Difference, that we might make a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Report thereof to the Quarterly Meeting which had imployed us.</hi> And this being in the Forenoon, we deſired another Meeting in the Afternoon of the ſame Day, with the Friends of the Town. This was not only propoſed openly, but <hi>A. B.</hi> was deſired to bring with him what Friends he pleaſed: What could be fairer than this? Would any but a guilty Man have found fault with it? Yet againſt this <hi>A. B.</hi> exclaims grievouſly, and againſt us for it, as if never had the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury been done: Thus he ſets it forth, <hi>It's to be noted, that when</hi> O. S. <hi>with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Seven, ſaw that I was not ſatisfied to leave the Matter to them, though ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, as I thought, given them ſufficient Reaſon for it, that he, with the reſt, did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, the ſame Day, of their own accord, without either the Knowledge, Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, Conſent or Agreement of the Quarterly Meeting, appoint another Meeting, the latter part of the ſame Day, both contrary to all Methods, Order, Practice or Preſident
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151315:9"/>in the Caſe, ever heard of, or uſed, that I know of, amongſt us before,</hi> &amp;c. Is not this a <hi>Ridiculous</hi> Exception for any one to make, eſpecially for one that fain would paſs for a Wiſe Man? Would he have had us to have ſtaid near Three Months to have asked the Quarterly Meeting (which had left the whole Matter to us) whether if one Meeting about it would not ſuffice, we might appoint two? And whether, if we were not ſatisfied in the Forenoon, we might not meet again in the Afternoon? He carries on his Cavil further, blaming us for <hi>inviting both Men and Women, and they too only ſuch as we beſt liked and approved of.</hi> To the firſt I ſay, both Men and Women were proper to be preſent, for he had complained on behalf of others, as well as himſelf, who might be Women as well as Men, for ought we knew, and he would not tell us who, or what they were. To the latter I ſay, we ſhut out no Friends, but deſired the Company of ſuch eſpecially, as were moſt ſenſible of Truth's Concerns. Accordingly the greater part of the Friends (thoſe eſpecially that were moſt ſenſible of the hurt and miſchief of theſe Diſſentions) met with us, and when we had ſate together ſome time, waiting on the Lord in his Holy Fear, we deſired the Parties who were the Accuſers, and them alſo who were Accuſed, to withdraw, that we might enquire of the Friends concerning the ſtate of the Differences that were among them, and they might inform us the more freely. Accordingly <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> (who were the Accuſed) did withdraw: But the Accuſers (<hi>viz. A. B.</hi> and <hi>R. S.</hi>) refuſed to withdraw, but continuing among us, did ſtrive with much vehemency to hinder the Friends from giving us an account of the Differences, and by whom the Offences had entered, and were continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, (for that we deſired to know) according to the Knowledge and Senſe they had thereof. And this one would think, he <hi>(had he been in the Truth that is plain and innocent)</hi> would have been deſirous we ſhould know. But being guilty, this pinched him, and angered him; and in p. 4. of his Book, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, that we <hi>did then and there propoſe unto them this following intricate, improper, and impertinent Queſtion,</hi> viz. <hi>Whether</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. <hi>or</hi> A. B. <hi>himſelf, were the Cauſe of the Diſturbance that had happened in their Meetings?</hi> Was this an intricate Queſtion? Was it improper, or impertinent, to be known or asked? What Queſtion could have been more plain? What more proper and pertinent to be asked than this? But I perceive now he would have had us have asked another ſort of Queſtion, <hi>viz. Whether thoſe Articles and Charges that he had drawn up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. <hi>were in the Thoughts of thoſe Friends, true or falſe?</hi> Had that been a proper or pertinent Queſtion, I pray, when the Monthly Meeting, before which he had laid thoſe Articles and Charges, had not examined or enquired into them, but to free themſelves from the trouble and difficulty thereof, had referred them to the Quarterly Meeting? Nay, had it not been both improper and abſurd, for us to have put that Queſtion to the Friends, much more to have concluded any thing upon their Thoughts, concerning the truth or falſhood of thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Articles and Charges, when as A. B. who was the Author of them, refuſed to ſubmit them to us, or let us have the examining of them? Yet the Friends did ſeverally, according to the Experience they had, the Obſervations they had made, and the Senſe God had given unto them, declare, <hi>That</hi> A. Bonifield <hi>himſelf
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151315:9"/>was the man, that had frequently broken the Peace of the Publick Meetings, by ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at honeſt Friends, which had brought great Grief and Burden upon many tender Hearted ones. And that they did believe, that</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. <hi>were not ſuch men as he had repreſented them to be,</hi> viz. <hi>to ſeek to Exerciſe Lordſhip over their Brethren: But that by long Experience they had found them to be faithful, Conſciencious, Serviceable Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After we had received this Account from the Friends of the place; <hi>A. B.</hi> having utterly refuſed to bring the particular matters to an hearing before us, in order to be ended by us, we who were appointed by the Quarterly Meeting, withdrew among our ſelves, to confer together about the matter, and to draw up a Report thereof, to be made to the next Quarterly Meeting. And before we went away, it aroſe in our Hearts in the Love of God, to write a few Lines tenderly to <hi>A. B.</hi> to perſuade him to be quiet, which we did as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Abraham Bonifield,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the tender Love of God, deſiring the Peace and Welfare of thy Soul, and of all the Called of God, do we ſend theſe Lines to thee, to entreat and beſeech thee to ſtudy to be quiet, and keep low to the meaſure of God's Spirit given to thee to profit withal; and to forbear any more ſmiting at thy Fellow Servants, and diſturbing the Peace of the Meetings of God's People, to the grief of many tender hearted Friends, as hath evidently been mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to us this day before thy Face. Wherefore, we earneſtly deſire thee to be adviſed, and labour to amend what hath been amiſs, that thou mayeſt be reconciled to thy Brethren, before it be too late. We are thy Friends, heartily wiſhing thy Welfare.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Auſtel,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Gidding,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edmond Orpwood,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rich. Vokins,</hi> Jun.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Oliver Sanſom,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Potter,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Cooper.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Reading</hi> 
                        <date>the 24th of the 7th Month, 1690.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Beſides this, the Friends of <hi>Reading</hi> alſo, having a great weight and burden upon their Spirits, with reſpect to <hi>A. Bonifield</hi>'s deportment amongſt them, did between this time and till next Quarterly Meeting, ſend their Senſe in Writing to <hi>A. B.</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Reading</hi>
                        <date>the 25th of the 10th Month, 1690.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Friend <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE whoſe Names are under-written, being ſorely grieved, and having long born the burden of that wrong Mind and Spirit, in which thou haſt been ſmiting thy Fellow Servants, in our Publick Meetings, to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151315:10"/>great grief of our Souls, and likewiſe to the diſhonour of the Bleſſed Truth, and the Profeſſion of it. We ſay, we have long born in Patience that which is very hard for us to bear, hoping that the Labours, Advice and Endeavours of many Faithful Friends, might have had ſome place in thee. But to our Sorrow, we ſee thou lightly regardeſt it, ſtill perſiſting in that wrong Mind of diſturbing our Peaceable Meetings. Oh, Friend, we are troubled for thy ſake; and for the Honour of Truths ſake, we do intreat thee to obſerve that Doctrine thou ſo often repeateſt, that is, to be reconciled to thy Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou offer thy Gift; and ſo come to be reconciled in the Unity of the Spirit, which is the Bond of Peace. And this is earneſtly deſired by thy Friends who deſires thy Welfare.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>This was Signed by <hi>William Speakman</hi> and 21 Friends more of <hi>Reading</hi> Meeting.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The next Quarterly Meeting was holden at <hi>Newberry</hi> on the 5th of the 11th Month, 1690. At which an Account being called for, of the matter committed by the laſt Quarterly Meeting to us, even relating to <hi>A. B.</hi> &amp;c. Report was made thereof according as we had found it, which the Meeting taking notice of, and being concerned both for the Honour of Truth, the Peace of the Church, and the recovery (if poſſible) of the Man, did agree to ſend two Friends of the Meeting to viſit him, and endeavour to make him ſenſible of his Miſcarriage, and the hurt he had done thereby. Accordingly a Minute of the Meeting's Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon, was entered in the Meeting Book as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Newberry</hi>
                        <date>the 5th of the 11th Month, 1690.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas there was ſomething offered to the laſt Meeting by <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi> of his diſſatisfaction with ſome Proceedings of ſome Friends of their Monthly Meeting at <hi>Reading;</hi> and the Meeting judging it moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, did agree and make choice of ſome Friends, to hear and determine the matter, who accordingly did meet at <hi>Reading,</hi> at the time appointed about it; accordingly an Account is now given by the Friends concerned, that when they were ſo met on the account of that Service, <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi> inſtead of bringing forth his Charge or Complaint, did read a Paper of Excuſes, to ſhew cauſe why he would not commit his Caſe, or give it up to the Friends as appointed by the Quarterly Meeting, and agreed to by himſelf. And judged the <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> to be Unjuſt, Uncharitable and Immoral in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings herein, and ſo refuſed to give up his Caſe to be ended by them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is now the Judgment of this Meeting, That his Carriage herein, in ſlighting the <hi>Quarterly Meeting's</hi> Judgment, and breaking his own Agreement, is contrary to the Truth. And <hi>John May</hi> and <hi>James Mathew</hi> are deſired to ſpeak with him, in order to admoniſh him to acknowledge his Miſcarriage herein, and to give ſatisfaction to the <hi>Quarterly Meeting,</hi> and come into Unity with Friends.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151315:10"/>
            <p>At the next <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> which was holden at <hi>Reading</hi> on the 4th of the 3d Month, 1691. <hi>John May</hi> and <hi>James Mathew</hi> gave an Account, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deſire of the laſt Meeting, they had ſpoken with <hi>A. Bonifield,</hi> and that he did fignifie to them, <hi>That he was troubled that it had ſo come to paſs, that the Friends appointed before, had made a Journey in vain through his occaſion.</hi> And <hi>A. B.</hi> himſelf, being then preſent, did ſignifie the ſame to the Meeting; adding, That if Friends would accept of it, he would be content to bear the Charge of their Journey, or to that effect. And after ſome Diſcourſe about the Differences, <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> did offer it up again to the Meeting, to be ended by the ſame Friends before appointed, who being all preſent, except one, and <hi>Benjamin Antrobus</hi> of <hi>London</hi> happening to be there, <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> deſired that he might be put in the room or ſtead of that other Friend that was abſent: To which the Meeting, with <hi>A. B</hi>'s conſent, did agree. And thereupon, after the <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> was ended, we ſeven who were appointed for that Service, did meet the ſame day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and had a full hearing of the matters in difference, <hi>A. B.</hi> reading ſeveral large Writings containing Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> all which being <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> heard, <hi>duly</hi> weighed, and <hi>well</hi> conſidered of, in the Fear and Counſel of the Lord, we gave our Senſe and Judgment upon the whole matter, according to the Underſtanding we had received from God therein. Which Judgment being drawn up in Writing, and Subſcribed with all our Names, we ſent a Copy thereof to <hi>A. Bonifield,</hi> which is as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>VVHereas we whoſe Names are hereunto Subſcribed, at the requeſt of <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi> and by the conſent of the <hi>Quarterly Meeting,</hi> held at <hi>Reading,</hi> the 4th of the 3d Month, 1691. were to hear the Complaints and Grievances of the ſaid <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> and others, againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and to put an end to all differences between them; and accordingly, after a deliberate Hearing and Examining the many Articles, Complaints and Charges, fully and impartially of the ſaid A. <hi>B.</hi> againſt the others, which being meaſured by the Line of Truth, and weighed in the right Ballance, there appeared little of Subſtance in them; and after a ſerious conſideration thereof, and waiting in the Light of Chriſt our Lord, the Senſe and Judgment we have received, is on this wiſe, That A. <hi>B.</hi> hath not herein been Exerciſed in the pure peaceable Wiſdom that is from above, but in the Earthly, Senſual Wiſdom, hath been watching over his Brethren with an Evil Eye, and ſeeking occaſions againſt them, and hereby hath much darkened and hurt himſelf, for which our Souls are grieved: Therefore our tender Advice is again renewed, to beſeech him in Bowels of Love, to wait in Humility and Quietneſs upon the Lord, that in his meek and lowly Spirit he may come to be reconciled to his Brethren: For our farther Senſe is, That until this be witneſſed, he ought not to offer his Gift upon God's Altar. Alſo our Senſe and Judgment is, That he ought to deliver up to be deſtroyed, all his Papers and Writings that do relate to, or contain matter of Charges, Complaints, or Reflections againſt his Brethren <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and that he ceaſe and forbear Writing any more of the like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151315:11"/>evil and hurtful tendency, which we are ſenſible can produce nothing but ill conſequences; and have been gathered together and treaſured up, not by that Spirit wherein the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel ſtandeth, and Bond of Peace is kept, but in a wrong Spirit out of the Counſel of God. And moreover, our Senſe and tender Advice to all Friends concerned, is, That in all things they walk circumſpectly, in the tenderneſs and gentleneſs of the Love and Life of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and be careful what in them lieth to cut off all occaſions of offences from any that may ſeek it, and endeavour to remove the Blocks as much as they can, out of the way of them who are in danger of ſtumbling.</p>
                  <p>And as touching Buſineſs, Meetings, and Recording matters there concluded, our Senſe and Judgment is, That if any omiſſion or ſhortneſs have been, it ought to be acknowledged and amended for the future. And as touching open Feuds, Heats and Contentions in Publick Meetings, our Senſe and Judgment is, That ſuch things are againſt the Intereſt of Truth, and tend to ſtumble and hurt the Weak, and ought by all Friends wholly to be avoided, and that all Reflections againſt each other in Publick, ought to be forborn as much as may be.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Potter,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Oliver Sanſom,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Auſtell,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Cooper,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Benjamin Antrobus,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Gidden,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Vokins.</hi> Jun.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Againſt this Judgment <hi>A.B.</hi> and <hi>R.S.</hi> exclaimed extreamly, calling it an Unrighteous Judgment. And when at the next <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> (which was at <hi>Newberry</hi> the 6th of the 10th Month, 1691.) it was read, <hi>A.B.</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, was ſo <hi>Clamorous</hi> and <hi>Troubleſome,</hi> that the Meeting could not well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in their buſineſs. For which reaſon partly, and partly becauſe ſome Friends were willing to try what might be done, to bring him to a ſenſe of his evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to repent thereof; that ſo the Recording of it might have been ſpared, it was not Recorded in the Book at that Meeting. (Which tenderneſs towards him, he hath ſince made an <hi>evil uſe</hi> of, falſly ſuggeſting, as if the Meeting was not ſatisfied therewith, and could not agree about Recording of it;) but at the next <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> following, it was Recorded by Order of the Meeting in the Meeting-Book: <hi>A.B.</hi> (who was preſent) behaving himſelf more like a Man bereaved of his Sences, than like a Sober Man, threatning a ſad Judgment that ſhould fall on Friends, if they did Record that Unrighteous Judgment (as he called it) for he by his great ſwelling words, would have frighted Friends (if he could) from doing it. But Friends ſaw his Spirit to be wrong, and Recorded the Judgment, which hath ſtood, and will ſtand over him, and let him twiſt or twine which way he can, he will never get from under it, unleſs he Repent.</p>
            <p>Thus Reader, I have given thee, as briefly as I could, a plain and true Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this Matter, ſo far as the <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> was concerned in it; by which thou mayeſt ſee a pretty deal of A. <hi>Bonifield's Shifting Tricks,</hi> the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his Temper, and the <hi>unrulineſs</hi> of his Spirit, which cannot reſt nor be quiet. He hath repreſented things in his Book far otherwiſe than in truth they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151315:11"/>were. But he is ſo hobled in the doing it, that from his own Book his Falſhood appears. He makes the ground of his refuſing to ſtand Tryal before thoſe Friends whom the <hi>Quarterly Meeting,</hi> upon his Complaint had (with his own conſent) referred it to; becauſe his Complaint was not openly read in the <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting.</hi> In this he diſcovers a great want both of Judgment and Sincerity. <hi>Had he not wanted Judgment,</hi> he might have ſeen, that as it was properly in the Power, and at the Diſpoſe of the <hi>Quarterly Meeting,</hi> whether a Complaint, not coming from a <hi>Monthly Meeting,</hi> but in a private manner, ſhould be read openly in the Meeting or no: So it was not reaſonable, that a Complaint againſt any Member or Members of the Meeting, ſhould be read openly in the Meeting, unleſs that Meeting had intended to have had the whole matter contained in ſuch Complaint Examined, Heard, Try'd and Determined in the open Meeting; which that Meeting did not think fit. <hi>Had he not wanted Sincerity,</hi> he would not have ſtarted back, and refuſed to ſtand to what the Meeting had Ordered, and himſelf had agreed to; much leſs would he have alledged this as a Pretence or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for his ſo doing, when-as he had conſented to ſubmit his Cauſe to be Heard and Determined by thoſe Seven Friends whom the Meeting had appointed thereunto, and the time was ſet for the hearing thereof, <hi>after he knew</hi> the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had refuſed to have his Complaint openly read. And he himſelf <hi>afterwards,</hi> at the <hi>Quarterly Meeting</hi> at <hi>Reading,</hi> in the 3d Month, 1691. <hi>without having his Complaint openly read,</hi> did offer to leave his Cauſe to the ſame Seven Friends, that had been before appointed by the Meeting, for them to hear and end it, which ſhews his Exception againſt them both before and ſince, was but a <hi>Shifting Cavil,</hi> and that he was <hi>void of Integrity</hi> in urging it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Reaſons (as he calls them) which he gives why he would have had his Complaint read openly; and why upon the not reading thereof, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſtand to the Meetings Order, and his own Agreement, doth ſufficiently manifeſt his own unreaſonableneſs; they are in <hi>p.</hi> 4, 5, 6. of his Book, where alſo he changes the Title of his Paper from a <hi>Complaint</hi> to a <hi>Petition,</hi> which word he repeats over and over, near half a ſcore times (I gueſs) and in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, calls it ſometimes (and moſt often) a <hi>Petition ſimply;</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Petition,</hi> or <hi>Complaint;</hi> and anon a <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Complaint;</hi> not knowing himſelf what he would be at: Or as if he knew not the difference between a <hi>Petition</hi> and a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, Charge</hi> or <hi>Impeachment.</hi> The fore part of that Paper which he calls, <hi>Something offered as the Reaſons of deſiring the publick Hearing or Reading of a Petition,</hi> &amp;c. (which begins in his 4th page) hath nothing in it of Reaſon, or that looks like Reaſon; let him aſſign any Sentence out of it if he can. After that in <hi>p.</hi> 5. he ſets a new Title thus; <hi>Here followeth ſomething upon a Second and more Deliberate Conſideration, what I now find my ſelf concerned and beſt ſatisfied to do;</hi> and ſo far is he from offering Reaſons in this, that it rather ſhews his reſolute Will, than Reaſon: To this, in his 6. p. he adds a <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> in which he ſays are <hi>Two weighty Reaſons for a Publick Hearing of the Petition; firſt, becauſe the Grievances therein contained, relate to the Monthly Meeting, ſo not a Private nor a Perſonal Concern.</hi> If this be true, it makes againſt him: For it is evident, the <hi>Monthly Meeting</hi> did not Imploy, nor Impower him to make Complaint, of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151315:12"/>any Grievances relating to them. He cannot, dares not, ſay they did; what then had he to do to exhibit a Complaint of Grievances relating to the <hi>Monthly Meeting,</hi> without the Order, Direction, or Appointment of the <hi>Monthly Meeting?</hi> Nay, without the Conſent or Privity of the Monthly Meeting? If he had not been a very <hi>Buſie Body,</hi> he might (one would think) have given the Monthly Meeting leave to have made their own Complaint of Grievances relating to them, if they had any. So that this is ſo far from being a Reaſon for him, that it is a Reaſon againſt him, weighty enough of it ſelf, to have juſtified the <hi>Quarterly Meeting,</hi> for not reading his Complaint openly in the Meeting. <hi>A.B</hi>'s ſecond Reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe every Member is equally concerned to exerciſe the Senſe and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding that God has given them.</hi> This I grant, but when a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is brought to a Meeting, and that Meeting agree to commit the Hearing and Determining thereof to a Select Number, ſurely then, no Member of that ſaid Meeting ought further to concern himſelf in that matter, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the whole Meeting.</p>
            <p>To manifeſt yet farther the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfairneſs</hi> of this Man, obſerve that in p. 3. he ſays, <hi>I never left my Caſe wholly unto them,</hi> viz. <hi>the Seven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or ſatisfied at all, nor any further nor otherwiſe neither, than as conſtrained and forced to what I did.</hi> When as all the Friends then preſent, know that he agreed with the Meeting in it. And his excepting againſt one (for the Meeting named eight at firſt) is an ARgument that he conſented to the Meetings Choice in the other Seven. But that which puts it out of all doubt is, that about half a year after, at the <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meteting</hi> at <hi>Reading,</hi> he offered to the Meeting to refer and leave his Cauſe to the Hearing and Determination of theſe ſame Seven Friends, whom the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had choſen before, and that no delay might be occaſioned, by the abſence of one of them, he himſelf named another Friend, and deſired he might be added to the Six, in the room of him that was abſent; which plainly ſhews, he <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed</hi> the Choice, and accordingly he went on to exhibit, and make out his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges before them.</p>
            <p>Yet he hath another ſetch, which looks with rather a worſe face than the former; for when he ſaid, <hi>I never left my Caſe wholly unto them,</hi> viz. <hi>the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c. he adds, <hi>To ſubject or ſtand to their Award, any otherwiſe than only condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and with this proviſo, if managed impartially and to ſatisfaction,</hi> p. 3. and p. 5. He ſays, <hi>Seeing a Publick Hearing of it could not be obtained, I condeſcended to the aſo eſaid; provided it was done impartially and to ſatifaction.</hi> And in p. 6. ſpeaking of his having condeſcended to refer the matter unto the aforeſaid for an Hearing, Ending, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he adds, <hi>yet not without a conditional Reſerve.</hi> Now doth not this manifeſt great <hi>want of Sinoerity</hi> in him, to pretend and make a ſhew of giving up his Cauſe, and leaving it to Friends to hear and end; and yet at the ſame time have a <hi>conditional reſerve</hi> in his Mind, <hi>a ſecret Proviſo,</hi> to let himſelf looſe by? Doth this agree with his writing himſelf <hi>Thine in the Truth that is plain, Innocent, and void of the beguiling Crafts of men?</hi> Surely one would think he writ that <hi>Craftily,</hi> that he might the more eaſily <hi>beguile</hi> thoſe that are indeed Plain and Innocent. Now pray mark what this private Condition, this Mental Reſervation, this ſecret Proviſo was; he gives it in theſe words, <hi>viz. If managed impartially and to ſatisfaction,</hi> p. 3. <hi>Provided it was done impartially and to ſatisfaction,</hi> p. 5.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151315:12"/>Who was to judge whether it was done impartially, but himſelf? And for whoſe ſatisfaction did he provide, but his own? Was not this an abominable <hi>Juggle</hi> and Abuſe, for him to pretend to give up his Caſe to Friends, and leave it to them to Hear and Determine, and yet keep a ſecret Reſerve in his Mind, that if he was not ſatisfied with the end they made, he would not ſtand to their Determination? This among Men of the <hi>loweſt</hi> Pretences, either to Religion or Common Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, is not counted Honeſt. He had better have told the Meeting at firſt, he would leave it to them, or ſuch as they ſhould chooſe, to end it, if they ended it to his ſatisfaction; otherwiſe he would Appeal from them, for ſo it ſeems he did intend from the firſt, as he intimates p. 5. <hi>I condeſended to the aforeſaid, provided it was done impartially and to ſatisfaction, elſe did intend</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to refer it, by Appeal, to the Yearly Meeting.</hi> And as he intended not to ſtand to our Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, unleſs it were to (his) ſatisfaction, ſo it ſeems as if he had intended alſo, before we medled with it, not to be ſatisfied with what we ſhould do in it. For in the Paper he had drawn up before we came to enquire into it, (and which, when we came, he read to us as his Reaſons for refuſing to let us med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it) he ſays, <hi>Seeing there was ſuch an irregular ſtep made in the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (by which he means the Meeting's not letting him read his Complaint in the open Meeting) <hi>we cannot reaſonably expect theſe few can either go on well, or end it, ſo as it ought to be to ſatisfaction.</hi> And ſo much had he poſſeſſed his Mind with that (or at leaſt pretended ſo) that when we came firſt to <hi>Reading</hi> about it, he would not open the matter to us, nor yield that we ſhould at all meddle with it. Now I deſire the Reader to obſerve and conſider the Nature, Temper and Spirit of this Man; <hi>how prone he is to Contention and Quarreling,</hi> and what contrivances he has, and what Proviſion he makes, to continue and perpetuate Diſcord and Strife; by excepting againſt the proper ways and means for ending it. For Experience ſhews it too ſeldom happens, when Differences fall out between Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Perſon, that ſuch an end can be made thereof, by the moſt Judicious and Indifferent Perſons that can be choſen, as will prove to the ſatisfaction of both ſides. Now if the Perſons differing (after they have left, or referred their Difference to others to end) ſhall be at liberty on either ſide <hi>to fly off,</hi> and refuſe the Determination made, becauſe they don't like it, or it is not to their ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, what end can be made of Differences? Surely this contrivance of his doth not proceed from the Peaceable Spirit of Chriſt: but from that Spirit which loves Diſſention and Diſcord, and would not willingly ever be without it, and therefore ſeeks, by all the ways it can, to encreaſe it and keep it up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> hath another Exception againſt us, and that I think ſnews his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as much as the former doth his Falſeneſs: He is angry that we gave any Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all, alledging, that we were <hi>appointed for Reconcilers (not Judges)</hi> but to hear and end all Differences betwixt them, ſo he has it in his Title Page. And p. 6. he ſays, <hi>It was not for a Sentence or Judgment, but for Juſtice and Equity, Hearing and Ending of all Differences, that it was committed unto them.</hi> And p. 3. he ſays, <hi>Neither yet would any Rational. Man think, the aforeſaid at their Meeting</hi> Reading <hi>(unleſs I were beſides my ſelf, or wholly infatuated) a Meeting inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d for Judgment, Sentence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but Reconciliation, Hearing and Ending all Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151315:13"/>us;</hi> would any Rational Man, that reads theſe Paſſages, think otherwiſe of him, but he was beſides himſelf, and wholly infatuated when he writ this? Did ever any Man before this, blame Referrees, or thoſe to whom the Hearing and Ending of Differences was committed, for giving Judgment or Sentence between the Parties differing? Would he have had the Difference heard and ended without Judgment? 'Tis a ſign he is a <hi>Man of ſmall Judgment</hi> himſelf. If any have a mind to have buſineſs done <hi>without Judgment,</hi> they may ſend for him. We were (he confeſſes) to hear and end all Differences betwixt them; but he thinks we were not appointed to judge between them. To what purpoſe do Perſons hear Differences, but to end them? How is it likely they ſhould end them, if they may not declare where the ground of the Difference lies? Which Party is in the right, which is in the wrong? Who is to be blamed, and for what? If they declare this, that Declaration is Judgment or Sentence. When Perſons differ, each comonly thinks himſelf in the right, and his Adverſary in the wrong; if neither can convince the other, then (becauſe none is fit to be Judge in his own Cauſe) recourſe is had to others, who are Authorized to Hear and Determine. That Determination is commonly made, by declaring which of the differing Parties is in the wrong, or does the wrong, and wherein. And that is called giving of Judgment. But it is a folly next to madneſs, to ſay, as he does, they were appointed to hear and end all Differences, but not for Judges, or to give Judgment. I have heard ſay, that the Commiſſion by which the Judges ſit to try Cauſes at the Aſſizes, is called a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and that thoſe words ſignifie to Hear and Determine. Now would it not be a wiſe buſineſs for ſuch an one as <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> (if there be any ſuch one) to tell the Judge, when he is to try a cauſe, That he is appointed not to Judge, but to hear and end the Cauſe in difference? But what makes <hi>A. B.</hi> ſo averſe to Judgment? Surely it is no Credit to his Cauſe, nor ſign of Innocency in him. He might have remembred <hi>David</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>The Mouth of the Righteous ſpeaketh Wiſdom, and his Tongue talketh of Judgment,</hi> Pſal. 36.30.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be obſerved, that after we had heard <hi>A.B</hi>'s Complaints and Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and had given our Senſe thereupon, and the Quarterly Meeting approving the ſame, had cauſed it to be Recorded in the Meeting's Book, <hi>A. B.</hi> raged extreamly, and troubled Friends, both in City and Country with his Letters and Papers, as his Book ſhews, where he has Publiſhed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of diverſe of them, to his own ſhame. In his 11th p. he hath Printed a Letter directed to the Friends of the Second Days Morning Meeting at <hi>London,</hi> filled with Complaints againſt particular Perſons, becauſe they would not own and joyn with him, when he took upon him to Preach and Pray in Publick Meetings, after he was gone into Enmity and Prejudice, and had rejected the Quarterly Meeting's Order, and broken his own Agreement. In his 12. and 13. pages he ſets a Copy of a Letter which he ſent to me, in which he very much abuſes me, as he doth often in his Book, endeavouring to faſten upon me, that at the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Newberry,</hi> in the 5th Month, 1691. after we had heard his Complaints, and given our Judgment on them, when he Appealed to the Yearly Meeting, I ſhould propoſe a Medium, that the Buſineſs ſhould be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151315:13"/>anew to ſome Ancient Friends at <hi>London.</hi> This he repeats many times over in his Book, with as much confidence as if it were true; whereas I never made any ſuch Propoſal, nor was it likely I ſhould, ſeeing I was one of the Seven, who had heard and given Judgment on the Difference before. But ſeeing, after his many Repetitions of this Story, and Cavils about it, he refers to the Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting's Book for proof, ſaying, p. 49. <hi>But yet if any may be doubtful of the Truth of what is here alledged, and ſo often cited by me concerning him and it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pray let ſuch have recourſe to their Quarterly Book, and the minute made upon it at the aforeſaid Meeting.</hi> Now though I was not doubtful, but certain that no ſuch Propoſition was made by me, I have ſearched the Quarterly Meeting's Book, that I might be the better able to ſatisfie others, and do find and declare, that there is no minute nor mention in the Meeting's Book, of any Propoſition made by me, or by any other Member of the Meeting, for <hi>A. B.</hi> to Appeal or Refer his Cauſe to either the Yearly Meeting, or any particular Friends. And all that is entered in the Meeting's Book, at the Quarterly Meeting, with reſpect to the Buſineſs of <hi>A. B.</hi> is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That
<q>the Friends appointed by the Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting, to hear the Complaints and Charges of <hi>A. B.</hi> againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and to put an end to all Differences between them, did give account that accordingly the ſame ſame day, they had a full Hearing of the whole matter, both of <hi>A. B</hi>'s Papers and Charges, and <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B</hi>'s Anſwers. And when they had conſidered of the matters in the Counſel of the Lord (according to that meaſure of his Spirit and Wiſdom given to them) they drew up a Paper containing their Judgment upon the whole matter as before-mentioned, which Paper was now read.</q> Now judge, Reader, whether this be not a very wicked Man, to forge ſuch a falſe thing, and to endeavour to faſten it upon me, and to revile and abuſe me thereupon, ſo ſhamefully as he hath done through his Book, when he had no ground for it: And to refer to the Quarterly Meeting's Book for proof of it, when there is no mention of it there. And indeed, all that I can remember that was ſaid at the Quarterly Meeting about it, was but this, when he threatned the Meeting that he would carry it by Appeal to the Yearly Meeting, or would lay it before ſome Ancient Friends, and named <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>S. C.</hi> I made anſwer to this effect, That <hi>whitherſoever he carried it, I did not doubt but all honeſt Friends that ſhould have the hearing of it, would have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with us in what we had done in the mateer.</hi> And this evil minded man, hath the confidence to affirm over and over, that at the Meeting I propoſed his laying of it before ſome Ancient Friends at <hi>London,</hi> and that I named <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>S. C.</hi> on his part. But his own Confuſion, and ſelf-contradiction, ſufficiently ſhews the falſeneſs of his Story. For whereas at that Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Newberry</hi> in the 5th month, 1691. he threatned to Appeal to the Yearly Meeting, and ſays, p. 14. That I thereupon propoſed, as a medium, a <hi>Referrence</hi> to ſome Ancient Friends at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> he ſays in his 12. p. that the Letter he ſent to me, at the time of the Yearly Meeting at <hi>London,</hi> was in order for me be aſſiſtant with him in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the <hi>Appeal,</hi> propoſed by my ſelf at the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Newber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> Here he makes as if I had propoſed his <hi>Appealing to the Yearly Meeting.</hi> But in his Letter to the Monthly Meeting at <hi>Reading,</hi> (dated near nine months before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151315:14"/>this, though placed after in his Book) he makes as if I had propoſed <hi>a Referrence to ſome ancient Friends,</hi> as a medium to prevent his threatned Appeal to the Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting. And yet in his ſaid Letter afterwards to me at <hi>London,</hi> having men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned his being (as he ſaid) neceſſitated to Appeal, he propoſes this Referrence as a new thing, thus, <hi>But to prevent nevertheleſs, the more Publick notice and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, if thou pleaſe, we may the rather endeavour to have it referred to a certain number of ancient Friends,</hi> &amp;c. Thus he is in and out, ſtaggering and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with himſelf. Yet upon this falſe ſuggeſtion, that I propoſed this Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; he abuſes me at his pleaſure. In his 13th p. he ſays, when he ſpake with me after the ſame manner (at <hi>Gracious-ſtreet</hi>) as he had written, <hi>I ſeemed as a man ſurprized, and one amazed, as not knowing what to anſwer or ſay for my ſelf, but ſpeedily ſought for ſome Houſe or Place to get away and hide my ſelf from him.</hi> I did not know before, that he counted himſelf ſuch a <hi>terrible Body,</hi> that the ſight of him ſhould fright me; nor do I yet know any thing I have done, for which I need to hide my ſelf from him, or any one elſe, (though the company of ſuch a quarrelſome man is not deſirable to any one that loves Peace.) But this which he hath ſaid of me here, is modeſt in compariſon with what he ſays in p. 42. where he repeats this matter (for he loves to repeat things often over, that he may make the more noiſe) there he ſays thus, <hi>No ſooner had I ſpoken to him of it, but he immediately haſted and ruſhed away from me as a man affrighted and ſurprized, looking one way and another for his flight and ſpeedieſt getting away, and much like</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to the Thief (if I may uſe ſo pertinent a Simile) that deſires the dark and ſhadow of the Evening to cover and hide himſelf from the light and diſcovery of the day.</hi> How well this Language and Simile becomes him, I leave to the Reader to judge. But for all his repreſenting me ſo ſurprized and amazed at his Preſence, one might think he was in ſome great maze himſelf when he writ that Letter to me. For beſides it is nonſenſical throughout, he gives this for his Reaſon, why he would have the Difference then heard at <hi>London,</hi> viz. <hi>To prevent thoſe ſad and evil effects it hath already brought forth.</hi> I thought thoſe effects that are already brought forth, had been paſt preventing, But this is like him.</p>
            <p>Beſides this Letter to me, he has Printed another which he writ to the Friends of the Monthly Meeting at <hi>Reading,</hi> and would read it to them, though it was after the Judgment given againſt him. After that, he Printed another which he brought to the Quarterly Meeting in the 8th month, 1692. and had the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to preſs to have liberty to read it in the Meeting, though he had abuſed and vilified the Quarterly Meeting before, and Appealed (as he ſays) from them to the Yearly meeting. Theſe ſerve to diſcover his own Folly and froward Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. But that which is moſt ſtrange, is, that after he had ſo often declared how much he was in Conſcience concerned to ſtand up againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> for Uſurping Authority, Rule and Lordſhip over Friends and Meetings, and had ſet forth his Charges in the moſt aggravating terms; He now tells us of <hi>an Offer</hi> he made to <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B. of a free and voluntary forgiving and paſſing by of all Offences,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without either mentioning or bringing up of any of the Cauſes or Grounds of the Difference.</hi> Nay, he doth not ſo much as mention any ſhew of Sorrow, or token of Repentance, as a condition for this free forgiving and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151315:14"/>by of all Offences. By this it may be gueſſed what a ſort of Concern it was that he had, and how little there was of Conſcience in it. Yet he ſays, he was <hi>hearty and in good earneſt,</hi> and ſays, A. H. R. <hi>and</hi> M. S. <hi>can witneſs that he was ſo, who were Eye and Ear-witneſſes of it.</hi> But though they might be Eye and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes of his Propoſals, methinks they ſhould hardly undertake to be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his being hearty and in good earneſt. However he ſeems to impute the unſucceſsfulneſs of this, to <hi>W. L</hi>'s asking him impertinent Queſtions, (as he calls them) <hi>about the frame and temper of his Spirit, and whether he was in a fit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſo to propoſe.</hi> One would think a Man that were in a good frame, and of a right Temper of Spirit, would not have counted that an impertinent que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>Upon this I perceive he began to bend his Mind towards Printing. For the next thing in his Book, p. 16, 17. is, <hi>The Copy,</hi> (he ſays) <hi>of a Letter he ſent to</hi> G. W. <hi>and</hi> S. C. <hi>in order for their help and aſſiſtance, and to ſtop and prevent Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> A long <hi>ſcribble</hi> he troubled them with, and to make them amends for it, ſuggeſts, (p. 18.) as if they had loſt, or pretended to have loſt, his Papers of Charges, Complaints, Grievances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would be tedious, as well as needleſs, to take notice of all the impertinent Letters and Papers he has Printed in his Book. Therefore paſſing by ſome, I take notice that in a Paper without date, called, <hi>Some offers of Peace once more propoſed to</hi> W.L. J.B. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 19, 20. he returns to his pretence of Conſcience; and nothing leſs will ſerve his turn then, in order to Reconciliation with <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> than <hi>their confeſſing themſelves guilty of thoſe high Charges he had before exhibited againſt them,</hi> which he elſewhere tells us, are <hi>Crimes of an High and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Nature.</hi> Yet in p. 22. he ſays, at a Meeting which he had with ſome Friends at <hi>London,</hi> he did ſign a Paper, <hi>containing a free and voluntary forgiving of</hi> W. L. <hi>and</hi> J. B. But immediately adds, <hi>In which I was neither clear, nor at all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, becauſe neither Repentance manifeſted, nor any Satisfaction given to me, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aggrieved and offended.</hi> How ill doth this agree, with his fore-cited offer to freely and voluntarily paſs by all Offences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without either mentioning or bringing up any of the Cauſes or Grounds of the Differences, which he brought <hi>A. H. R.</hi> and <hi>M. S.</hi> to witneſs, that he was hearty, and in good earneſt for? No mention in that Paper of their Repenting, Confeſſing, or giving him Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. But in this other which he ſigned at <hi>London,</hi> he was neither clear, nor at all ſatisfied, becauſe neither Repentance manifeſted, nor any Satisfaction given to him.</p>
            <p>But in this, as in moſt things, he is not without a reſerve: For though he did ſign that Paper at <hi>London,</hi> yet he <hi>intended not in the leaſt to hurt or give away his Cauſe, wound or boggle his Conſcience thereby;</hi> and why? <hi>Foraſmuch as the Crimes wherewith they are charged are of an High and Criminal Nature;</hi> viz. <hi>Spiritual Pride, over ruling of Meetings, and Lording it over Friends.</hi> Yet as High and Criminal as he calls theſe, he could but a little before, without wounding or boggling his Conſcience, make an offer of freely forgiving them, without any Terms of Repentance or Satisfaction. One would think when he was ſo ready and eaſie at propoſing Forgiveneſs, if he was <hi>hearty and in earneſt</hi> in it, he did not <hi>in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151315:15"/>believe, they were guilty of ſuch high and criminal Matters as he now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents them His next words open him a little further; <hi>It is to be noted</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that this my ſo large (if not too large) condeſcention to ſuch their deſire, was only complied unto by me, upon the apprehenſion or (as I thought) aſſurance of Friends being engaged to ſee that</hi> W.L. <hi>and</hi> J.B. <hi>ſhould do the like:</hi> And a little lower he ſays, <hi>I do declare, and that in the preſence of God, that I had never ſigned that Paper of theirs, had I not thought that they looked upon themſelves as ingaged, and would not have been concerned to have written down to</hi> W.L. <hi>and</hi> J.B. <hi>for them to do and perform their part (as I had done mine)</hi> &amp;c. This is indeed to be noted, but not for his Credit. This ſhews how <hi>void of ſincerity</hi> he was in what he did, and that <hi>he did not act Conſcienciouſly,</hi> but politickly <hi>(with the beguiling Crafts of Men)</hi> thinking that by his ſigning that Paper, he ſhould have engaged the Friends that met with him to have brought <hi>W.L.</hi> and <hi>J.B. (who were innocent)</hi> under the ſame Circumſtances with him <hi>who was guilty.</hi> But here, it ſeems, his Policy failed him, and that has made him Rage the more.</p>
            <p>About Three Months after this, I obſerve (from p. 23.) that <hi>G. W.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Reading, A. B.</hi> gave him ſome <hi>now</hi> trouble about his <hi>old</hi> Buſineſs, and through importunity got him to hear ſome of his Complaints; whereupon <hi>G. W.</hi> wrote a few Lines, as tenderly and favourably for him as could be: Yet that did not pleaſe him. He rejects that, as <hi>not being impartial, nor yet ſuch as with which his Conſcience could be ſatisfied.</hi> However he drew up a Paper the next Day, and delivered it to <hi>G. W.</hi> inſtead of his, of which he ſeems ſo highly conceited, that he not only ſays, <hi>it might, if truly made uſe of, and put in due practice among Friends, really tend to a true, juſt and laſting Peace and Amity between both them and him;</hi> but propoſes it likewiſe as <hi>a true and Chriſtian Method to be made uſe of, by and among all Friends every where,</hi> &amp;c. This one would think ſhould be ſome notable thing; or elſe that he is notably conceited of his own doings. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of ſeveral Heads, of which the firſt is this; <hi>viz. The beſt way to lay a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of true and laſting Peace among us, is to fix Judgment upon that which is wrong, where-ever it is.</hi> What a Childiſh Man is this, that breaks his own Head by contradicting himſelf, in almoſt every thing he undertakes! When we by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Quarterly Meeting (and with his own conſent) had heard his Complaints and Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and their Defence, and thereupon gave Judgment for putting an end to their Differences; he, becauſe we fixed Judgment upon him, who was wrong, not only exclaimed againſt that Judgment, (unjuſtly calling it wicked and unjuſt) but cried out moſt vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt us alſo, for giving any Judgment at all; ſaying, <hi>We were appointed for Reconcilers, not Judges;</hi> and <hi>that it was not for a Judgment or Sentence, but for Juſtice and Equity, Hearing and Ending of all Differences, that it was committed unto us.</hi> Now, all on a ſudden, he is <hi>for fixing Judgment, as the beſt way to lay a Foundation for a true and laſting Peace.</hi> But then this Judgment muſt be of <hi>his</hi> fixing, and that not upon what is wrong, but upon what he will call wrong. For in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Heads of his Paper, he makes himſelf Judge, between himſelf and thoſe he differs with, <hi>peremptorily determining, that they have been the unpeaceable and unquiet Men; and directs, that they ſhould he as far diſowned as he has been. And as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151315:15"/>for the Judgment of the Seven,</hi> (which is indeed the Judgment of the Quarterly Meeting, both as the Seven were appointed by that Meeting, and as that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath Ratified that Judgment, by Recording it in their Book among the Acts of the Meeting) <hi>he declares it to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous, Partial, and Arbitrary in it ſelf, and would have it to be revers'd, and utterly exterminated; ſee his Paper in</hi> p. 24. So that for ought I ſee, that which he calls the beſt way to lay a Foundation of true and laſting Peace among us, is, to let one of the differing Parties be Judge over the reſt, and let him determine what is wrong, and fix Judgment upon that. But how far this would be from being a Foundation of true and laſting Peace, there is none, I hope, (beſides himſelf) of ſo little Judgment, as not to ſee.</p>
            <p>That which follows next in <hi>A. B</hi>'s Book, is, Obſervations both General and Particular upon that Paper, which we Seven, who were appointed by the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting drew up, as our Senſe or Judgment upon the Differences; which Obſervations take up ſome eight Pages, or more, of his Book, and are filled with Railing, Reviling, Bitter Expreſſions, Unchriſtian Language, and ſuch Envious Reflections, without any ſolid Matter, or fair Reaſoning, but a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Juſtifying himſelf by meerly ſaying ſo, without Proof or Demonſtration, that I do not think any Sober Man can Read them without great diſlike; therefore I do not hold it worth my while, to refute each particular which he hath written in thoſe Obſervations of his; his own Work therein ſufficiently refuting it ſelf. Yet that the Reader may ſee, that I have cauſe to ſpeak of them as I do, I will give him one Inſtance, by which he may judge of the reſt. It is in p. 28. and in his ſecond Obſervation, where having ſet down theſe words in our Paper, relating to himſelf; <hi>viz. Therefore our tender Advice is again renewed, to beſeech him in Bowels of Love to wait in humility and quietneſs upon the Lord, that in his me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k and lowly Spirit he may come to be Reconciled to his Brethren,</hi> &amp;c. On this <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> Advice, he makes this <hi>harſh</hi> and <hi>rugged</hi> Obſervation. <hi>The greateſt piece of Folly,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Weakneſs, and ridiculous Nonſenſe, I think, that ever any Man was injoined.</hi> Would one not think this Man Mad, not only to call beſeeching, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining; but to call it the greateſt piece of Folly, Weakneſs, and ridiculous Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, to beſeech a Man in Bowels of Love to wait in humility and quietneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on the Lord, that in his meek and lowly Spirit he may come to be reconciled this Brethren? Yet he ſticks not at this, nor ſtops here, but adds, and (it is) <hi>ſo diculous, the Caſe conſidered, that it rather beſpeaks the ſcorn and deteſtation of all than any notice to be taken of it, by all that cannot be thus beſeeched and bowelled out their Wits and right Senſes, the Matter in charge conſidered, which is True, and no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> What a paſſionate Spirit is this? What, to ſay it beſpeaks the ſcorn and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eſtation of all, to but beſeech one in Bowels of Love to wait in humility and q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>neſs upon the Lord, that in his meek and lowly Spirit he may come to be rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iled to his Brethren; and to reckon them out of their Wits, and right Senſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will take any notice of it? Then he goes on; <hi>Was ever the like falſe, corrupt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> injurious Judgment, Injunctions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>given forth againſt, or injoined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> Here he ſtops, and ſays, <hi>And this I think ſufficient at preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve occaſion to infer further upon the ſame under the ſeveral other Heads;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151315:16"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151315:16"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151315:17"/>yet according to his uſual inſtability and uncertainty, he runs on again, adding to the ſame Obſervation, thus, <hi>And would not the Papiſts themſelves as much tender, bowel, and beſeech, to make a Man turn Hypocrite, Lie, and Betray the Truth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And may it not as truly be ſaid of you as formerly,</hi> viz. <hi>That your tender Mercies, Bovels, and Beſeechings, is Hardheartedneſs, Severity, and Cruelty?</hi> Judge now, Reader, whether the words he cited out of our Paper, as our tender Advice to him, deſerved ſuch an Obſervation, as this he hath made upon them. And by this thou may'ſt alſo gueſs at the reſt, for they are much-what after the ſame ſtrain.</p>
            <p>In his 7th Obſervation, p. 29. he Cavils at our delivering <hi>our Senſe, that until he be reconciled to his Brethren, he ought not to offer his Gift upon God's Altar.</hi> Here he <hi>carps</hi> at the words <hi>[God's Altar]</hi> and ſays, <hi>If I muſt not offer it upon God's Altar, and Chriſt Jeſus be that Altar, then I pray you upon what other Altar ought I to offer it?</hi> Anſwer, Upon none; while in ſuch an unreconciled ſtate, but ſeek Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation firſt. <hi>I hope,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you cannot barr up Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Anſwer, 'Tis his own Quarrelſome Spirit, that hath barred up Heaven to him and his Offerings, while he remains in that unreconciled State. He adds, <hi>I am ready to believe, it is the firſt time, that ever any Man was forbidden the Offering his Gift upon God's Altar.</hi> Hath he never read, or had he forgot, what Chriſt ſaid on that ſubject, in his Sermon on the Mount? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. <hi>Therefore if thou bring thy Gift to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and there remembereſt that thy Brother hath ought againſt thee; leave there thy Gift before the Altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy Gift.</hi> Was not this God's Altar, that they were then to offer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And were they not here poſitively forbidden to offer their Gifts upon God's Altar, unleſs they were firſt reconciled to their Brother? How came he then ſo readily to believe, that it is the firſt time that ever any Man was forbidden the offering his Gift upon God's Altar? Surely what Chriſt ſaid to ſome other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villers, might not unjuſtly be applied to him. <hi>Ye err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God, Mat.</hi> 22.29. Had he known and conſidered this aright, he would not have <hi>taunted</hi> us, as he doth, ſaying, <hi>I pray you from whence derived you, or any Man on Earth any ſuch Authority, except from</hi> Rome, <hi>to ſo limit and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join me to ſilence, whoſe Mouth the Lord-hath opened, eſpecially under theſe, or ſuch Circumſtances; or to thus endeavour to limit or quench the Spirit of God in me?</hi> &amp;c. For he might have ſeen that this Authority (if he will needs have it ſo, though we exerciſed no Authority over him, but beſought him in Love) was derived higher than from <hi>Rome,</hi> or any Earthly Man, even from the Heavenly Man Chriſt Jeſus. Nor is it the Mouth which the Lord hath opened, that we would have ſhut or ſilenced; but that Mouth of his which the Enemy hath opened to reproach, revile, and ſpeak evil of the Faithful Servants of the Lord; neither did we endeavour to limit or quench the Spirit of God in him: But we deſired he would endeavour to limit and quench that Spirit which <hi>luſted in him to Envy,</hi> Jam. 4.5. by joining with which he had before <hi>grieved,</hi> and in a great meaſure <hi>quenched,</hi> the Spirit of God in himſelf. But to ſet this more home upon him, ſince he ſays, he is ready to believe it is the firſt time, that ever any Man was forbidden the offering his Gift upon God's Altar, I will remind him, that in a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151315:17"/>Letter of his own to <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> dated the 23d of the 6th Month, 1690. he puts the ſame thing upon them thus, <hi>viz. I deſire of you in the mean time, that according to the good Advice of our Lord Jeſus, and Order of the Holy Truth profeſſed by us, that ye forbear the further offering of your Gifts, until you have made Satisfaction to your Brother;</hi> Was he for barring up Heaven then?</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of the remainder of his Book, (after theſe Obſervations of his) is levelled more particularly againſt me, though he has not been ſparing to caſt his <hi>Envious Darts</hi> at me throughout the whole; yet becauſe in many places of his Book, and particularly in theſe Obſervations, he ſpeaks ſo much, and ſo often of his Charges againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> aggravating them with high Terms, and laying much weight upon them, I think fit (before I enter upon my own particular Defence) to ſpeak briefly to them, that the Reader may ſee how cauſleſs his ſo great Complaints and Clamours are.</p>
            <p>He hath divided them into Ten Articles; of which the firſt is, <hi>Their Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary-like Over-ruling of Monthly Meetings.</hi> His Proof for this, is, That they <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively affirmed, that a Matter under Debate (at a Monthly Meeting in the firſt Month,</hi> 1690.) <hi>ſhould not be the act of the Meeting. And although when ſo made, and record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that afterwards they ſtill as apparently denied it to be the act of the Meeting.</hi> This was, it ſeems, about treating with <hi>I. C.</hi> about opening the Meeting-houſe Doors (which <hi>T. C.</hi> and the reſt of the Separates, had wrongfully ſhut up) and A. B. in a forward <hi>buſie mind</hi> (having got a few others to join with him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) would needs be <hi>tampering</hi> (as I underſtand) with <hi>T. C.</hi> about opening them, and would have done it in the Name of the Monthly Meeting, which <hi>W. L.</hi> (not <hi>Jo. Buy,</hi> for <hi>Jo. Buy</hi> was not preſent at that Meeting, as appears by the Monthly Meeting's Book) objected againſt, deſiring, that if they would needs be medling in that Matter, it might not be done as the Act of the Meeting, but as their own Act, many of the Meeting being diſſatisfied with it, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting againſt it. And ſurely in a Caſe of that Importance (for it was, A. B. ſays, <hi>to deſire them to open the Doors freely, or upon refuſal, to offer them all their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi>) wherein the whole Meeting muſt have been concerned, it had been but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to have had the Conſent and Agreement of the Meeting before it had been undertaken, at leaſt before it had been made or declared to be the Act of the Meeting. I obſerve he ſays here, that when it was ſo made (<hi>viz.</hi> in his Senſe the Act of the Meeting) and ſo Recorded (though no ſuch Record appears) in the ſaid Book, <hi>they ſtill denied it to be the Act of the Meeting.</hi> And well they might, for there is no ſuch Record thereof in the Book.</p>
            <p>The Second Article of his Charge againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> is, <hi>Their paſſing a raſh and unchriſtian Sentence</hi> (ſo he calls it) <hi>upon him, as being a Man of a wrong Spirit, and that they ſaw and diſcerned him to be ſo: As alſo their comparing him to thoſe they counted open Apoſtates, one run out from Truth, Brother to</hi> Bugg, <hi>and like to</hi> Rogers <hi>and</hi> Story, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If they judged him a Man of a <hi>wrong</hi> Spirit he hath ſaved them the labour of proving it, having too evidently proved it himſelf ſince, by the <hi>wring</hi> Work he hath imployed himſelf in, and the <hi>wrong</hi> Fruits he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151315:18"/>hath brought forth, of Envy, Strife, Hatred, Contention, Railing, Backbiting, Slandering, Lying, and the like, which ſhews their Judgment in the Caſe was neither raſh, nor unchriſtian, but ſound and chriſtian; and their ſight and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning therein was true and right. And if they compared him to open Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, ſuch as <hi>Bugg</hi> or <hi>Rogers,</hi> he hath made the Compariſon good, (by appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he hath now done) an <hi>open Enemy in Print,</hi> as thoſe before-named had done before, whom he once counted and called open Apoſtates, as well as <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>A. B.</hi> And what they accounted him then, may well be gueſſed, by what one of them (<hi>viz. T. Curtis</hi>) called him, who meeting him on the way, did (as <hi>A. B.</hi> himſelf related it) thus accoſt him, <hi>viz. Canker, go thy way Canker.</hi> But now he hath altered his Tone, and doth not call them <hi>open Apoſtates,</hi> but thoſe that <hi>others counted as open Apoſtates.</hi> And it was time for him indeed to change his Note, now that he is not only fallen in with that Party who have owned thoſe Apoſtates, and ſpread their Books, but is alſo fallen into the ſame ſort of Work, which thoſe open Apoſtates were in long ago. But by comparing the time when he ſays <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> called him a Man of a wrong Spirit, (which he ſays was on the 22d and 24th of the 4th Month, 1690.) with the time of his Exni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting theſe Charges againſt them (which was on the 26th of the 6th Month, 1690.) it ſeems as if he drew up thoſe Charges againſt them meerly to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on them, for calling him a Man of a wrong Spirit.</p>
            <p>His third Article is againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> only, and that <hi>for refuſing him the ſight of the Monthly Meeting Book.</hi> This may eaſily be Anſwered, becauſe <hi>W. L.</hi> had no Order from the Meeting ſo to do. Nor is it proper for any Member of a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to whoſe keeping the Book is intruſted, to let any other Member, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally one known to be Contentious, to have it without the Meeting's Conſent; neither can any other Member ſay, as <hi>A.B.</hi> doth, that he hath as much Right and Property to have it, as the Perſon to whom by the Meeting it is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And whereas he ſaith the ſaid Book was at no time <hi>denied him</hi> by the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he might as well have ſaid at no time <hi>granted him</hi> by the Meeting: But when he adds, <hi>Or through any Diſſatisfaction of other Friends belonging to it,</hi> he ſtretches too far, as it is well known to moſt of the Meeting.</p>
            <p>His fourth Article is againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> jointly, falſly Charging them with <hi>Endeavouring to Diſmember him, Tying up his Tongue,</hi> &amp;c. This is an <hi>Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous</hi> way of ſpeaking, which he wickedly uſes to <hi>beguile</hi> his Reader into a belief, as if ſome act of <hi>Violence</hi> had been offered or threatened to him. But this I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak to hereafter, where he inſiſts more largely on it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſs it by here.</p>
            <p>His fifth Article is, <hi>Their diſorderly breaking up and leaving of Monthly Meetings before the Buſineſs had been near done, and when Matters have been juſt under Debate among us.</hi> For which he gives ſeveral inſtances, one of the 26th of the 6th Month, 1690. when he laid theſe Charges againſt them before the Monthly Meeting, for which he refers to his Paper of Complaint. But that Paper of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151315:18"/>Complaint gives no account of any ſuch diſorderly or indirect breaking up of that Meeting (that I obſerve) but it ſays, <hi>ſome Hours were ſpent in Conference about that Matter.</hi> Yet I think if Friends ſhould hold and continue their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as long as ſuch a <hi>Make-bait</hi> would hold them in <hi>Debate,</hi> they would find that much more diſorderly, than to break up their Meetings in <hi>ſeaſonable time,</hi> whether ſuch <hi>Cavillers</hi> are ſatisfied or no. He gives another inſtance alſo of a pretended diſorderly breaking up of a Meeting in the 5th Month, 1691. which appears no more than the former. But it appears by this that he has varied, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered or added to his Charges, ſince he gave them to the Monthly Meeting, and theſe which he has now publiſhed, are not directly the ſame which he brought to the Monthly Meeting; for how could he inſtance the 5th Month, 1691. in a Charge exhibited in the 6th Month, 1690. Eleven Months before?</p>
            <p>His ſixth Article is, <hi>Their encouraging and promoting at leaſt, if net firſt projecting, as he conceives, ſeveral Papers drawn up and ſigned againſt him.</hi> This is very idle and ſilly. He grounds their projecting (as he calls it) of thoſe Papers but upon his own <hi>Conception,</hi> but for their incouraging and promoting them, he offers not ſo much as that, as little worth as that is. But if they had incouraged the ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Papers, yet ſo long as thoſe Papers contain nothing but what is true, what Evil had they done in that?</p>
            <p>His ſeventh Article is, <hi>Their cauſing of great Diſorders and Diſtractions in our publick Meetings for Worſhip, by breaking up and diſſolving them in the time of his Teſtimony and Prayer.</hi> If any Diſorder was occaſioned thereby, he was the Cauſe thereof, by <hi>impoſing</hi> upon the Meeting his Teſtimony (as he calls it) and Prayer, which Friends had no Unity with, but deſired him to forbear, ſeeing him to be of a <hi>wrong</hi> Spirit, and of a contentious, quarrelſom Mind; reflecting on, and ſmiting at Faithful Friends in that which he calls his Teſtimony, which was <hi>his</hi> Teſtimony indeed, not <hi>Truth's</hi> Teſtimony, and therefore was by Friends in Truth Teſtified againſt. The time he ſets for the thus breaking up of Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (when he would have held them beyond the uſual time) being the 16th of the 1ſt Month, 1690. The 26th of the ſame Month, 1691. The 13th of the 7th Month, 1691. ſhews, both that this was after he had run out againſt Friends of the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings, and Judgment had been given againſt him; and alſo (as before) that theſe Charges are not the ſame, which he brought to the Monthly Meeting againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> in the 6th Month, 1690. In the cloſe of this Article he Names Three other Friends, <hi>viz. William Speakman,</hi> and two Women, for no other Cauſe (ſo far as I ſee) but that he might thence take occaſion to throw ſome of his Dirt upon them; which he doth thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though obſerve</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the firſt of them</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> W. S.) <hi>charged, and that by one of his own Children with Barbarous Severity and Cruelty towards his Wiſe and them.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>of being with Child before ſhe was Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ried.</hi> The laſt, <hi>permitted as a Preacher among them, and a profeſſed Friend too for nigh Twenty Years, and yet not come ſo far as to ſpeak the plain Language.</hi> How true this Charge upon the laſt is,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151315:19"/>I do not know, nor ſhall go about to excuſe. For if any one after ſo long Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Truth, is not come ſo far as to ſpeak the plain Language, ſuch an one is greatly to be blamed. But yet <hi>A. B.</hi> is more to be blamed, who after a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time of Profeſſion, is ſo far <hi>gone from</hi> (if ever he was come to) <hi>Plain-deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as to deal abuſively, and falſly by others, as his late Book makes appear, In his Charge againſt the ſecond, of being with Child before ſhe was Married, he has manifeſted an unchriſtian, bad Mind, thus to rake up a Miſcarriage done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Twenty Years ago, and for which the Woman hath long ſince given evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Tokens of hearty Sorrow, and unſeigned Repentance, not ſeeking to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her ſelf, or leſſen her fault, but plainly and honeſtly confeſſing her Offence, condemning her ſelf, and readily offering to do whatſoever ſhe could for taking off the Reproach from Truth. And hath ever ſince, (ſo far as I have underſtood) walked honeſtly and blameleſly in her Converſation, being much bowed down in Spirit under the Sence of that Tranſgreſſion. And had not A. <hi>Bonifield</hi> been an <hi>Enemy to Truth,</hi> and not only <hi>void of Chriſtianity,</hi> but of common Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Civility, he would never have revived the remembrance of ſuch a groſs thing (after it had been ſo long forgotten, as well as forgiven) thereby to bring the Reproach thereof afreſh upon the Truth, and to renew the Grief thereof to an already afflicted Woman.</p>
            <p>In the other part of this Charge of his, relating to <hi>W. Speakman,</hi> he is both Envious and Unjuſt; for the Matter he here charges him with, was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Monthly Meeting above Three Years and a half ago, and <hi>W. S.</hi> upon Examination thereof, was found to be Innocent. The Matter (as I find by the Monthly Meeting Book) was thus, on the 26th of the 5th Month, 1692. one <hi>John Veale</hi> brought to the Monthly Meeting a Paper, containing a Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>W. Speakman,</hi> for giving undue Correction to his Child, and for irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Carriage in his Family. Whereupon the Meeting ordered <hi>Daniel Bulluck, Andrew Hall, John Buy,</hi> and <hi>John Thorne,</hi> to hear and examine the Matter, and make Report thereof to the next Monthly Meeting. Accordingly they did meet about it at <hi>Daniel Bulluck</hi>'s Houſe, and having heard and examined the Matter on both ſides, as fully as they could, they made Report thereof to the next Monthly Meeting, on the 30th of the 6th Month, 1692. as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>WHereas <hi>John Veale</hi> at the laſt Monthly Meeting gave in a Paper, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>William Speakman</hi> is charged with giving undue Correction to his Child, and irregular Carriage in his Family. And we whoſe Names are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-written, being appointed to Examine into the ſaid Charge; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly being met at <hi>Daniel Bullucks</hi> Houſe, and upon the beſt Enquiry we can make, we do not find that <hi>William Speakman</hi> is guilty of the ſaid Complaint, neither can we find, that his Carriage in his Family hath been either unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, or unbecoming the Profeſſion he makes. And whereas <hi>John Veale</hi> has made his Report to others, before he ſpake of it to him, to the Scandal of the ſaid <hi>William Speakman,</hi> therefore in ſo doing, it is our Senſe, that <hi>John Veale</hi> herein hath done unfriendly by <hi>William Speakman,</hi> and not according to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151315:19"/>Goſpel Order. And further we do underſtand, that <hi>John Veale</hi> brought out this Charge by the inſtigation of others.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Thorn,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Andrew Hall,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Buy,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Daniel Bulluek,</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Judge now Reader, whether <hi>A. Bonifield</hi> be not a bad Man, in thus Publickly accuſing a Friend of barbarous Severity and Cruelty towards his Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when the matter had been brought before a Monthly Meeting above three weeks before, and upon full enquiry therein, the Friend was found and declared Innocent.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To manifeſt yet farther the falſeneſs of the Charge, <hi>William Speakman's</hi> Wife de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that theſe few lines following may be added.</head>
                  <p>WHereas <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> hath charged my Husband <hi>William Speakman</hi> in his Book Printed in 1695. with barbarous Severity and Cruelty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Wife and Children. Theſe are to certifie all to whom his Book may come, That his Charge is falſe and wicked, and therein he hath abuſed my dear Husband, who hath been and is tender and loving to me and his Children. To which I ſubſcribe, the 28th day of the Month called <hi>February,</hi> 1695.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Elizabeth Speakman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>A. B.</hi> his Eighth Article againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> is, <hi>Their ſetting up an open Standard of Oppoſition and Diviſion in our Publick Meetings, by their ſitting and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on their Hats in time of Prayer,</hi> which in p. 19. he calls <hi>an evil and irreverent Practice.</hi> But doth but herein condemn himſelf, and ſtrikes at them through his own Sides: For as evil and irreverent as he thinks it is, it was <hi>his own Practice formerly</hi> towards thoſe Separates (with whom he now joyns) <hi>as a Teſtimony of his not owning their Preaching or Praying then.</hi> Therefore he ſhould have Publiſhed his <hi>Recantation,</hi> for that, before he had fallen ſo foully upon others for the like. But he hath not ſtated his Charges right nor fairly, in taxing them with ſitting and keeping on their Hats in time of Prayer. That is too general; and being ſo, is not true, as himſelf knows; and All, that know their Practice, know, that they do not uſe to ſit or keep their Hats on, when any one is in Prayer, whom they have Unity with. And whenever they do keep on their Hats in time of Prayer, it is becauſe they do not own the Perſon Praying, or pretending to Pray. Which is the ſame Reaſon he himſelf uſed formerly to give, why he kept on his Hat, at the Prayer of thoſe others, which now 'tis like he puts it off to. Now, if Perſons whoſe common Practice is to put off their Hats in Prayer, do keep on their Hats at ſuch times only, when a Perſon <hi>thruſts himſelf upon them,</hi> taking upon himſelf to be the Mouth of the Meeting to God in Prayer, as well as the Mouth of God to the Meeting in Preaching, and ſo will <hi>impoſe his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Praying</hi> upon a Meeting, as if he were in Unity with, and owned by that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151315:20"/>Meeting, when indeed he is not, the keeping on the Hat at ſuch times, and in ſuch Caſes, is no Evil nor irreverent Practice; but it would look more like an <hi>Hypocritical Practice</hi> to put it off.</p>
            <p>His Ninth Article is, <hi>Their refuſing to take his Money, which</hi> (he ſays) <hi>he laid down at a Monthly Meeting towards a Collection.</hi> What reaſon had he to expect they ſhould take his Money, when (as in his Second Article he ſays) they had told him, they ſaw him to be a Man of a <hi>wrong Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tenth and Laſt Article of his Charge, is againſt <hi>J. B.</hi> in particular, and is thus worded, <hi>For his wicked and moſt Blaſphemouſly affirming, That he did ſee my Inſide; as likewiſe that he diſcerned my Heart and Inward Parts; which Wicked, Proud and Preſumptuous words of his, I do not look upon</hi> (ſays he) <hi>or can conceive to be at all leſs, or other than plain and abſolute Blaſphemy, and taking to himſelf the Power and Attributes only and alone proper and due to the Immortal God.</hi> This he <hi>harps</hi> upon in other parts of his Book, and makes a great noiſe about. Now, tho' I underſtand he hath ſtretched the words beyond what <hi>J. B.</hi> ſpoke, yet taking them as he hath laid them down, I think he will be hard put to it to find Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy in them. It is true, that it is the Lord that ſearcheth the Heart; but it is alſo true, (and methinks he ſhould not deny it) that God who ſearcheth the Heart, both can diſcover, and ſometimes hath diſcovered the ſecret Thoughts and Purpoſes of one Man's Heart to another. When <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul, I will tell thee all that is in thine Heart,</hi> 1 Sam. 9.19. Was that Blaſphemy? Or did did he ſpeak <hi>Wicked, Proud, Preſumptuous Words?</hi> When <hi>David</hi> ſaid of his Enemies, <hi>There is no faithfulneſs in their mouths, their inward part is very wickednefs,</hi> Pſal. 5.9. Did he ſpeak at randon, or at a venture? Or had the Lord diſcovered their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part</hi> to him, and let him <hi>ſee their inſide?</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias, Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lye to the the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> Acts 5.3. And, <hi>why haſt thou conceived this thing in thine heart?</hi> Ver. 4. Did he not <hi>diſcern the heart</hi> of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias?</hi> And ſee what he had conceived in his Heart? When the ſame Apoſtle told <hi>Simon, Thy heart is not right in the ſight of God,</hi> Acts 8.21. Did he not <hi>diſcern</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon's <hi>heart,</hi> and ſee his <hi>very inſide?</hi> Did the Apoſtle take to himſelf the Power and Attributes only and alone proper and due to the Immortal God? Did he ſpeak plain and abſolute <hi>Blaſphemy?</hi> Or <hi>Wicked, Proud</hi> and <hi>Prefumptuous</hi> words? If God hath in former Ages diſcovered to his Servants, the Hearts and ſecret Purpoſes of evil minded men; will <hi>A. B.</hi> deny that he can and may do ſo ſtill? His Hand is not ſhortened. And A. <hi>B.</hi> ſays, p. 6. <hi>We know for certain, that God is not limited to Parts nor Perſons.</hi> So that what he has done of old, he may do again, and that by the meaneſt, as well as by the higheſt Member in his Church. Has A. <hi>B.</hi> forgotten, that amongſt the excellent Manifeſtations which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reckons up, as wrought in man by the Spirit of God, one is <hi>Diſcerning of Spirits,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.10. Was that to give ſight of the <hi>outſide</hi> only, or of the <hi>inſide,</hi> Heart and <hi>inward parts?</hi> But there is beſides this, an underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the <hi>inſide,</hi> partly by the <hi>outſide</hi> (or Fruits brought forth) a knowledge of the Tree by its Fruits. And ſo apparently uvil are the Fruits A. <hi>B.</hi> hath brought
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151315:20"/>forth, that one may ſafely ſay; (and <hi>J. B.</hi> did not ſay ſo before) he ſees his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and diſcerns his Heart to be corrupt and naught, without danger of uttering Blaſphemy, or ſpeaking Wicked, Proud, or Preſumptuous words.</p>
            <p>Thus I have briefly touched the ſeveral Articles of his Charge againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> which he laid ſo much ſtreſs upon, calling them, <hi>Crimes of an high and criminal nature.</hi> But how light and trivial they are, in reſpect of the noiſe and buſtle he hath made about them, I doubt not but every intelligent Reader will ſoon and eaſily ſee. He adds, that he had alſo <hi>ſeveral other Articles in Charge againſt</hi> W. L. <hi>and which were alſo as material as theſe, and very little varying from the ſame Subject.</hi> If they varied but little from the ſame Subject, they might ſoon be as material as theſe, and yet be <hi>immaterial</hi> enough, or ſufficiently void of ſolid matter or ſubſtance. And therefore he had no cauſe to quarrel with us for declaring in our Judgment, that <hi>his many Articles, Complaints and Charges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meaſured by the Line of Truth, and weighed in the right Ballance, there appeared little of Subſtance in them;</hi> eſpecially conſidering that (as hath been noted in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral particulars before) he hath added many things to them ſince: Yet he hath ſo little Wit, as thereupon to ſay, p. 26. <hi>If ſo</hi> (viz. that there appears but little Subſtance in them) <hi>then the leſs to be blamed.</hi> But I think every Judicious man will think him the <hi>more</hi> to be blamed, for drawing up a Charge in ſo many Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and making ſo great a clutter about them, that had ſo <hi>little Subſtance</hi> in them.</p>
            <p>I come now to that part of his Book which is levelled more directly, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly at me, beginning at p, 33. where he ſays, <hi>Seeing that</hi> O. S. <hi>one of the aforeſaid unjuſt Judges, hath taken a freſh occaſion to thus run out againſt me, through ſome offence he has taken at my late Book of Queries, it hath come into my thoughts to further diſcover and manifeſt him, and that in his plain and naked ſhape.</hi> And tho' in p. 45. he reproacheth Friends with being <hi>like them of old, who ſaid, Report, and we will Report it:</hi> Yet now <hi>to his ſhame,</hi> he doth profeſſedly undertake to make this diſcovery of me, ſaying thus, <hi>viz. Not only from the Evidence and Proof from his own Mouth and Pen, but alſo from the Allegations, Reports and Accounts of others concerning him,</hi> &amp;c. And accordingly he hath dealt by me, expoſing what he hath picked up <hi>by Report</hi> (as in p. 37. line laſt) <hi>or Hear-ſay</hi> (p. 39.40.) againſt me, and where even that hath been wanting, or not full enough to anſwer his <hi>Envious</hi> Intention, he hath endeavoured to make it out with his own <hi>Surmiſes</hi> and <hi>Suppoſitions,</hi> no leſs than three times in one page, p. 40. And this he pretends to do ſaying thus, <hi>viz. To the end that all may know that he is not changed from what he was, but is ſtill and remains in the like Spirit of Malice and Bitterneſs, as is common, frequent and inherent</hi> (he ſays) <hi>to my nature.</hi> Now I obſerve how he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoots himſelf through his ill will to me, and runs himſelf upon a Rock before he is aware. For if (as he ſays) <hi>I am not changed from what I was, but the Spirit of Malice and Bitterneſs is inherent to my nature;</hi> then I was always ſo heretofore, and he muſt know it heretofore, and yet who more forward in pretence and ſhew of Love, Friendſhip and Unity with me than he, till of late years, ſince for my gently reproving him for his contentious quarrelling, he hath turned againſt me, and ſet himſelf to abuſe and defame me? Many lines of this nature are in his Book, which containing nothing but meer Clamour, I paſs it over as unworthy of any notice.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151315:21"/>
            <p>The occaſion he here takes for his particular Cavils at me, is from my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning him a former Book of his (which he had ſent me) and which I had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſomething on. It was a Book of Queries, and one part of the Title of it was, <hi>Plain and Honeſt Dealing.</hi> When I had read the Book, I found it to be ſo far from <hi>Plain and Honeſt,</hi> that I ſtruck out thoſe two words, and in their places wrote two others, more agreable to the Matter and Subſtance of the Book, <hi>viz. Falſe and Treacherous.</hi> I writ alſo ſomething on the Book, and ſomething on a Paper fixed to it, as my Senſe both of him and it; and having ſo done, ſent the Book back to him again. In all which I conceive I did him no wrong, with reſpect either to the matter I writ, or manner of doing it. As for the matter, he doth but nibble and carp at ſome words and paſſages in it (and that how idly, ſhall be ſhewn anon) but doth not undertake to Anſwer it. As to the manner of my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (which he ſeems to wrangle about) I think I did him no wrong. For he having (not lent but) <hi>given</hi> the Book to me, it was my own, and at my own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe, to uſe as I pleaſed; to add, or blot out what I would, and make what Alterations I ſaw meet. And when I had ſo done, it was in my choice either to keep or give it away, and I choſe to give it him again, and accordingly did ſend it him. I intended to have Publiſhed what I had Written and ſent to him with his Book, but conſidering the Subject treated of there does vary from this, I think fit to forbear at this time, and if occaſion offers, and way be made, there poſſibly may be a full Anſwer to it hereafter; ſo for the preſent I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to go through with my Anſwer to this Book.</p>
            <p>Now to manifeſt the <hi>Folly,</hi> as well as <hi>Malice,</hi> of this <hi>Cavilling</hi> Man, he hath picked two paſſages out of thoſe two Papers of mine (he mentioned p. 33. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which he was willing to undertake to Anſwer) and having moſt <hi>diſhoneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wreſted</hi> them, to a <hi>ridiculous</hi> as well as a <hi>wrong</hi> Senſe, he fills two pages (34. and 35.) with <hi>empty</hi> noiſe and clamour, in a <hi>confuſed</hi> manner, and <hi>nonſenſical</hi> heap of words, one of the paſſages he takes out of the latter part of my before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Paper fixed to his former Book, wherein I juſtly blamed him for his abuſive wreſting thoſe words, which he ſays <hi>J. B.</hi> ſpoke to Friends concerning him, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>if they could not bind or tie his Tongue, they would their own,</hi> which I told him could import no more in any tollerable Senſe or Conſtruction, than to this effect, that <hi>if they could not prevail with him to be quiet, and ceaſe contending with and diſturbing them, yet they would let him alone, and not ſtrive with him.</hi> The other paſſage he takes out of that which I wrote upon the Book it ſelf, where having ſhewed him the dangerous ſtate he was in, by entertaining hatred againſt <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> which he had evidently manifeſted by his endeavouring to ſlay their Chriſtian-Reputation, and ſo was by the Apoſtle judged to be a Murderer (<hi>He that hateth his Brother is a Murderer,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.15.) I asked him thus, <hi>For how couldſt thou deviſe to do them ſo much miſchief (and not hazzard corporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) as to expoſe them as thou haſt done?</hi> Here becauſe I quoted this Scripture, he inſinuates as if I intended Murdering of the Body, when my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was no other than as in the very line before, ſlaying their Chriſtian Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Yet by a ſtrange ſort of <hi>perverſe, abuſing</hi> and <hi>wreſting</hi> of words, he hath inferred from this, that I would have <hi>Bodily puniſhment inflicted upon him for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151315:21"/>writing his Books:</hi> And from this and the former Expreſſion (uſed he ſays by <hi>J. B.</hi>) of <hi>tying his Tongue</hi> (which had in it no more either of danger or hardſhip to him than to themſelves) for the words it ſeems were, <hi>If we cannot tye his Tongue, let us tye our own;</hi> that is, if we cannot perſuade him to hold his Tongue and not interrupt us: Let us hold our Tongues, and not anſwer him. I ſay from theſe two Expreſſions he hath run himſelf into ſuch a <hi>fright,</hi> as if he began to feel either the <hi>Whip,</hi> or the <hi>Fire</hi> already; ſo true of him is that which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith of the workers of Iniquity, <hi>They were in great fear where no</hi> (cauſe of) <hi>fear was,</hi> Pſal. 53.5. Hereupon he cries out, p. 34. of me, for <hi>ſcaring or affrighting him with Corporal or Bodily Puniſhment.</hi> And in p. 49. he very gravely (if there can be <hi>gravity</hi> in ſo great <hi>folly</hi>) ſays thus, <hi>And it might not I believe; be amiſs (if but or the Truths ſake) that ſome ancient and grave Friends would be and were ſo concerned, as to examine and know of</hi> O.S. <hi>what manner and degree of Puniſhment it is to be or muſt be, that my Body is to ſuffer or to be puniſhed withal for the great miſchiefs,</hi> &amp;c. And towards the bottom of the ſame page, he mentions again my <hi>uſing ſuch ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring threats of Corporal Puniſhment, or Puniſhments upon his Body.</hi> 'Tis well he is ſo apprehenſive of Bodily Puniſhment, that the fear of that may deter him from attempting that which might ſubject him to it: But it is ſtrange to ſee how upon theſe meer and willful <hi>Perverſions,</hi> he runs out in a noiſe of Words againſt <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> ſetting forth not only the <hi>heinouſneſs</hi> thereof, but the <hi>hideouſneſs</hi> thereof, and repreſenting to himſelf and his Reader, no leſs than <hi>moſt cruel Sufferings, and exquiſite Tortures; yea, and in the end death it ſelf. And before that, binding of Head, Tongue, Hands, Feet, the uſe and cruelty of the Gag,</hi> and whatever elſe he could think of, to heighten his <hi>affrighted fancy, the Coat and Hat of fearful and affrighting painted Devils, Hell and Hell-fire, put upon them,</hi> &amp;c. And all this noiſe and out-cry he makes for nothing, or without any cauſe or ground given him; but meerly from an <hi>evil mind</hi> and deſire in himſelf, to brand me and other Friends with being of a Perſecuting Spirit, than which there is nothing we are more againſt. But in this I doubt not but both his <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, and the Reader may from hence take notice what a <hi>Captious, Cavilling</hi> nature this Man is of, and how little he is to be regarded.</p>
            <p>From my altering with my Pen the Title of his former Book from <hi>Plain and Honeſt Dealing</hi> (which he did not uſe) to <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealing</hi> (which it plainly appears he both then did, and ſtill doth uſe) he takes occaſion to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign my Converſation ſaying, in p. 37. <hi>Becauſe</hi> O. S. <hi>hath ſo injuriouſly abuſed my true and honeſt Title,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I ſhall make a little farther enquiry, as an Addition to the former, of his manner of Life, Actions, Converſation,</hi> &amp;c. How well this becomes him, and with what mind he undertakes it, I ſhall leave the Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>He begins his Enquiry in a <hi>high</hi> and <hi>haughty</hi> Stile, thus, <hi>Firſt I ſhall demand of him</hi> (meaning me) <hi>to anſwer for himſelf in the Caſe of</hi> Dorothy <hi>and</hi> Nicholas Hall <hi>of</hi> Ludcum <hi>in the</hi> Vale <hi>of</hi> White-Horſe. From them or one of them he hath received he ſays, <hi>near a dozen Letters, and all of them chiefly and principally relating to his</hi> (meaning my) <hi>Falſeneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt and Treacherous Dealings towards the aforeſaid; for of Oppreſſion</hi> (he ſays) <hi>with cries for Juſtice, is the Tenor of the whole, and as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported,</hi> the ſame in effect throughout the whole County within the reach of my Power
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151315:22"/>and Juriſdiction.</hi> By this it appears, that as in natural Bodies, that are diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, the evil humours flow together: ſo in Bodies Civil or Religious, the evil humoured Members flock together, and Communicate their diſcontents one to another. <hi>A. B.</hi> underſtood that <hi>N. H.</hi> and his Wife had taken offence againſt me, how <hi>buſie</hi> thereupon was he, to <hi>flſh</hi> out of them, whatever he could think might make againſt me. On the other hand, they underſtood he had taken of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at me: How ready and <hi>forward</hi> were they thereupon, to <hi>furniſh</hi> him with their Complaints, and falſe Accuſations againſt me; ſee what an intercourſe has paſſed between them. Near a dozen Letters he has received from them, <hi>and all againſt me.</hi> How many he had ſent them, he doth not tell us, but he don't uſe to be behind hand at Scribling. The Tenor of their Letters, it ſeems, was of <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> with <hi>Cries for Juſtice,</hi> (againſt me) no wonder therefore that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſpoke <hi>ſo big,</hi> and took ſo confidently upon him to <hi>demand of me to anſwer for my ſelf,</hi> if he had been ſo often <hi>complained to,</hi> with <hi>Cries for Juſtice.</hi> This was enough to elevate one of his temper, and make him think himſelf <hi>ſome Body.</hi> But he has marr'd all, while to gratifie his Envy, he has extended this Cry for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice throughout the <hi>whole County,</hi> and that upon no better ground than <hi>Report,</hi> ſaying, and <hi>as reported, the ſame in effect throughout the whole County,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Beſides the ſeveral Letters which he received from <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Dorothy Hall</hi> to himſelf, he had alſo, it ſeems (incloſed therein) the Copies of Letters ſent by them to me, as he intimates, p. 39. out of which he Prints ſeveral fragments, in p. 38, 39, 40, and 41. intermingling other matters between; which both makes confuſion, and manifeſts he was in confuſion when he did it. However, I intend to ſpeak to this buſineſs (or <hi>Caſe</hi> as he calls it) of <hi>N. Hall</hi> and his Wife firſt, and afterwards to other things in their order. He begins in p. 38. with <hi>a Branch</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>in a Letter from</hi> Dor. Hall <hi>to me,</hi> which he ſays was to this effect, <hi>That ſhe was deeply concerned for two of her old Acquaintance,</hi> viz. <hi>for Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> Sion, <hi>that her Husbandry is managed no better, that her Harveſt was ſo ſmall,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Secondly, for</hi> Old England, <hi>that ſo much of her fair Building was moultring years ago, and now I have leaned</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>upon one of her props, and received an incurable wound: If her props be ſo feeble, it ſignifies her downfal is not long.</hi> By this the Reader may gueſs what a <hi>Whimſical</hi> Woman this is, and then he need not wonder that <hi>A.B.</hi> is ſo taken with her. He calls this <hi>her Innocent Simile,</hi> and takes upon him to apply it to me ſaying, <hi>This her Innocent Simile relates unto thee</hi> O. S. <hi>whoſe ill Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in the Lord's Vineyard hath ſo hindered the Harveſt or increaſe; and the Prop too, that they leaning upon, have given them ſuch an incurable wound, even thee,</hi> O. S. As to my Husbandry in the Lord's Vineyard, I have nothing to <hi>boaſt</hi> of: nor yet (I bleſs God) am I conſcious to my ſelf of any <hi>wilful default</hi> or negligence therein. However, it is my comfort, that I am not to give my Account thereof to <hi>A. B.</hi> whom it would better have become to have <hi>looked at home,</hi> and ſee how well he had diſcharged his own part in that for which he blames me: As to the former part of the Simile, if ever <hi>D. Hall,</hi> or <hi>A. B.</hi> either, was truly acquainted with Spiritual <hi>Sion,</hi> I doubt it is <hi>ſo long ago,</hi> and they have ſhewed ſo much <hi>unkindneſs</hi> to her ſince, that the acquaintance is worn out and loſt, but for the latter part of it; what can be more ridiculous, than to call me one of <hi>Old England</hi>'s Props!
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151315:22"/>For ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> expounds and applies it. One would think the <hi>incurable wound</hi> they ſpeak of, is in their <hi>Heads,</hi> and that it hath <hi>diſtempered</hi> both their <hi>Brains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fragments or pieces of Sentences which <hi>A. B.</hi> hath publiſhed out of <hi>N. Hall</hi> and his Wives Letters both to himſelf and me, being many and of divers kinds and matters, I ſhall not repeat them all, nor his Comments upon them. But the Subſtance of ſuch of them as relate to <hi>Hall</hi>'s own buſineſs, is to repreſent me as having wrong'd him and his Wife. In one of them (as A. <hi>B.</hi> hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it) he ſays thus, <hi>O. S. my cry is again for Juſtice, that the wrong that thou haſt done me and my Wife, may be put into the hands, of good and underſtanding Friends for a hearing, concerning thy unjuſt, unmerciful, and unchriſtian Actions,</hi> p. 39. In another thus, <hi>O. S, I not having Juſtice done me laſt ſecond day at</hi> Charloe (which was at the Quarterly Meeting) <hi>I do ſend theſe lines unto thee, to have the Money, that thy hard heart hath wronged me of.</hi> In another thus, <hi>I do greatly want what thee haſt wronged me of, to labour with my own hands,</hi> p. 40. In another thus, <hi>That O.S. through his Envy, and Cruelty had put him to almoſt five Pounds loſs, for leſs than Forty Pounds upon Land Security.</hi> upon which <hi>A. B.</hi> adds this, as his Comment, <hi>I ſuppoſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by his vexatiouſneſs at Law upon them, for I have heard he was very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From theſe foregoing, and other Paſſages of like tendency in <hi>A. B</hi>'s Book, a Stranger might think that I had <hi>greatly injured</hi> and wronged <hi>Nicholas Hall,</hi> that I had dealt <hi>extream ſeverely,</hi> and cruelly with him, that I had taken advantage upon him, had <hi>Circumvented, Cheated,</hi> or <hi>Oppreſſed</hi> him, to enrich or advantage my ſelf. That the Reader therefore may have a right underſtanding of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I will give a true and plain account thereof, and then leave it to his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>In the 4th Month, 1690. <hi>Nicholas Hall</hi> being <hi>Arreſted for Debt,</hi> and likely to be carried to Goal, his Wife (through much importunity, and by perſuaſion of ſome Friends) prevailed with me and <hi>William Auſtel</hi> (a Friend of <hi>Ore</hi>) who were both of us Truſtees for certain Orphans, and had ſome Money of theirs in our hands, to lend ſome of the ſaid Orphans's Money to <hi>Nicholas Hall</hi> to keep him out of Priſon, and he and his Wife did agree to Mortgage ſome Land (which was her Joynture) for the Security of the Money. Accordingly a Mortgage thereof was made to <hi>W. A.</hi> and me for one year, for 43 <hi>l.</hi> to the uſe of the ſaid Orphans: When this Money had laid about two years, the Children to whom it did belong, came to be of age to receive the ſaid Money, and we knew not how to come by it again: For by that time, <hi>Hall</hi> was in <hi>Priſon</hi> for Debt, and we had no way to raiſe the Money, unleſs we ſhould have ſeized on the Land that was Mortgaged for it; which we were unwilling to do, becauſe we would not uſe any Rigour towards <hi>Hall.</hi> So that we were neceſſitated to aſſign the faid Mortgage to one of the Children (and ſhe being a Woman and Married to one <hi>Francis Clarke</hi>) the Money due thereon, being part of her Portion: And to ſhew what favour we could to <hi>N. Hall,</hi> although there was near two years Intereſt due upon the Mortgage when we aſſigned it, yet we did not charge that to <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Clarke,</hi> to the intent that he might be the more kind to <hi>N. Hall,</hi> in reſpect of his Poverty.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151315:23"/>
            <p>This is in ſhort, the true State of the Caſe, by which it doth appear, that I helped <hi>N. Hall</hi> to Money at a <hi>pinch of need,</hi> and when he was in a <hi>great ſtraight,</hi> to ſave him from going to Goal. <hi>I never Sued him</hi> for the Money again, <hi>I never Seized the Land</hi> that was Mortgaged for it, (though the Mortage was forfeited by non-payment of the Money:) And he knows in his Conſcience, that I never received any Money at all on this account, firſt nor laſt from him, but one half years Intereſt for the Childrens uſe. Yet he charges me with having wronged him, and taxes me with Unjuſt, Unmerciful and Unchriſtian Actions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of me the Money which my hard Heart (as he falſly ſays) hath wrong'd him of. But whether he in thus belying and abuſing me, and <hi>A. B.</hi> in abetting him, and publiſhing his Lyes for him in Print, hath not groſly abuſed me, let the indifferent Reader judge.</p>
            <p>But <hi>A. B.</hi> is more to blame than ordinary, in this caſe. For before he Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed theſe falſe Charges againſt me, he knew they had been heard three times over, and I each time declared Innocent, and <hi>Hall</hi> was blamed for his cauſeleſs Clamours againſt me, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, at a Monthly Meeting, and afterwards at a Quarterly Meeting, as the Records belonging to the ſaid Meetings doth fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate.</p>
            <p>But ſometime before the ſaid Quarterly Meeting, I having heard, that <hi>N. Hall</hi> had been with <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> with his Complaints and Papers, and A. <hi>B.</hi> made a noiſe and pudder about it; I writ a Letter to him, and therein plainly and briefly ſignified the true State of the Caſe between <hi>N. Hall</hi> and my ſelf, and that I never did him any wrong, nor gave him the leaſt Cauſe or occaſion to complain againſt me: To this effect, very tenderly I wrote, to prevent his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abuſed by <hi>N. Hall</hi>'s falſe Stories. But alas, A. <hi>B.</hi> was ſo glad that he had catcht hold of ſomething, which he hoped would make againſt me, that ſo far as I can underſtand, he encouraged <hi>Hall</hi> in his Clamours againſt me, as much as in him lay: For I being at <hi>Reading</hi> in the 10th Month, 1694. about other buſineſs, <hi>N. Hall</hi> being brought in by A. <hi>B.</hi> his Advocate, intruded his impertinent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt me, and A. <hi>B.</hi> urged me much to make <hi>Hall</hi> ſatisfaction for the wrong which he ſaid I had done him. I told them both to this effect, That I never did <hi>Hall</hi> wrong, and that the matter had been already twice heard by Friends, and determined. But they were ſo eager upon me to have it referred, that (to leave them the more without excuſe,) I ſaid to <hi>N. Hall</hi> before ſeveral others, There is thy Neighbour <hi>Michael Malet,</hi> I am content that he ſhall hear the Matter, and to ſtand to his award. This <hi>Michael Malet</hi> is a Counſellor at Law, who lives in the ſame Town where <hi>N. Hall</hi> lives, a Man of note in the Country, and one that is well affected to Friends. With this offer of mine, <hi>N. Hall</hi> ſeemed greatly pleaſed, and ſo I left them. After I was gone, they (unknown to me) drew up a ſhort Paper, ſignifying that <hi>N. Hall</hi> and I had agreed to refer his Matter to <hi>M. Malet</hi> aforeſaid, and ſome that were preſent ſet their Hands to it, and ſent it to the ſaid Counſelor by <hi>N. Hall.</hi> And to back the bufineſs, A. <hi>B.</hi> ſent a Letter to him at the ſame time by the ſame Bearer, of which, having obtained a Copy I inſert it here, that the Reader may obſerve, how much this <hi>Envious</hi> Man <hi>buſied</hi> himſelf in that which did not concern him.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:151315:23"/>
            <p>The Letter was thus.
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Loving Friend, Counſellor <hi>Mallett,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AFter my true and engaged Love unto thee, and thy Wife, with thy Son, if at home. The occaſion of this is to inform thee, That thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Nicholas Hall</hi> being here at <hi>Reading,</hi> and the Caſe of the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and <hi>Oliver Sanſom,</hi> accidentally laid before ſeveral of us here, in order for a hearing, and to have Juſtice done him; whereupon it was agreed, that the Matter in Difference betwixt them ſhould be referred unto thee, to both determine and end it betwixt them. I therefore only intreat thee to do the poor Man Juſtice; for it is to be feared, that it hath been hard for him to obtain it hitherto. But if <hi>Ol. S.</hi> do refuſe it, or take any indirect way either to evade or prevent his having it, happily it will be ſeen that <hi>Nicholas</hi> can find ſome that will ſtand by him in his Caſe, ſo far as to do him Juſtice, though a Poor Man, and <hi>O. S.</hi> a Rich one.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Reading,</hi> 
                           <date>the 28th of the 10th Month, 1694.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Thy Loving Friend, <hi>Abraham Bonifield.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>By this Letter the Reader may obſerve how <hi>forward A. B.</hi> was, not only to <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> himſelf in other Folks Matters, but to reflect upon the Monthly and Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meetings, inſinuating as if <hi>Nicholas Hall</hi> could not obtain Juſtice there. Shortly after I being at a Meeting at <hi>Chawlow,</hi> where <hi>Counſellor Mallett</hi> alſo was, after the Meeting was ended, and before Friends parted, he acquainted them that he had received the aforeſaid Letter and Paper; and that inaſmuch as the Matter was referred to him, he was willing all ſhould know, that what he did therein ſhould not be Clandeſtinely, but openly, and above-board, or to that effect. And he deſired me to give him the true ſtate of the Caſe in Writing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I lived remote from him, and <hi>N. Hall,</hi> being his Neighbour, ſhould have liberty to make his Objections, and to repreſent his Caſe alſo; I therefore drew up the ſtate of the Caſe, in ſubſtance the ſame as I have given it here before, but more large, with the Circumſtances of it. And ſome time after the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor gave forth his <hi>Award</hi> or <hi>Judgment</hi> under his Hand, as followeth,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>HAving peruſed, well weighed and conſidered of this ſtate of the Caſe, between <hi>O. S.</hi> and <hi>N. H.</hi> (whereto as a Neighbour I have been no Stranger) I ſhould be ſhort to Truth and Juſtice, ſhould I not truly declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whomſoever may pleaſe to take notice hereof, That it is my <hi>Judgment,</hi> that the ſaid O. S. <hi>hath in all the Tranſactions thereof <hi>fully acquitted</hi> himſelf as a prudent and upright Perſon, and ought not to be perſecuted ſo cauſleſty by the ſaid</hi> N. H. <hi>by various Rumours to the contrary,</hi> as of late he hath done in divers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151315:24"/>places, after this Matter had been fully and freely diſcuſſed in an open and free Meeting at <hi>Weſt Chawlow,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Michael Mallett.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>About the ſame time, the Counſellor Judging it needful to inform <hi>A. Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> how he had found the right of the Matter to ſtand, wrote him a Letter in anſwer to that he received from him; a Copy of which here followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Loving Friend, <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAving not long ſince received from thee a Letter (without Seal) of the 28th of the Month laſt paſt. I take my ſelf to be under ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to diſabuſe thy (hitherto miſ-informed by <hi>N. H.</hi>) underſtanding, in relation to that Matter tranſacted between him and <hi>O. S.</hi> which I have not failed <hi>very carefully to examine,</hi> being invited thereto by the Subſcription of ſome Friends of <hi>Reading,</hi> whom I have ſome, though not much, knowledge of, but think worthy of ſuch ſatisfaction as well as thy ſelf, being to refer the Examination thereof to me; though <hi>I did think it needleſs,</hi> the ſame before having been publickly and fairly diſcuſſed, in a free and open Meeting at <hi>Weſt Chawlow,</hi> where were preſent divers very ſenſible, and I hope, very real Friends of thy Neighbourhood, and then ordered that the ſaid <hi>N. H.</hi> ſhould acquieſce: Though ſince he ceaſes not <hi>very caufleſly,</hi> to fill thine, and the Ears of others, with <hi>very unjuſt</hi> Complaints of O. S. who hath delivered to me the true ſtate of the Caſe in Writing, whereof I have Tranſcribed a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for his better Vindication, which may be at any time ready for thy view, when thou may'ſt think fit to make my Wife (who hath formerly given thee ſo much light as to this Affair, as might perhaps prevent any prejudice therein) and me happy with thy good Company here—where thou'lt not fail of an hearty Welcome from him, who is</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thy truly Loving Friend, <hi>Michael Mallett.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Ledencombe Regis,</hi> 
                        <date>9. <hi>Menſis</hi> 11. 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now if <hi>Abraham Bonifield</hi> had not been extremly darkened with Envy, how could he have dared to abuſe and ſlander me as he hath done in this Buſineſs of <hi>N. Hall,</hi> and his Wife, when at the ſame time, and before, he knew, that the Matter had been heard and examined by a Monthly Meeting of Friends, and I <hi>clear'd</hi> therein; that the Matter had been examined by a Quarterly Meeting of Friends, and I <hi>again cleared</hi> therein; that the Matter had a third time been heard and examined by Counſellor <hi>Mallett,</hi> (to whom it was partly through
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151315:24"/>
               <hi>A. B</hi>'s means referred) and I <hi>cleared</hi> therein, and the blame laid upon <hi>N. Hall</hi> for accuſing me without Cauſe.</p>
            <p>It is ſad to conſider that <hi>A. B.</hi> ſhould act thus againſt ſo clear evidence, and his own knowledge; but ſo far hath his Envy carried him, that he ſticks not to pervert the Judgment given by Counſellor <hi>Mallett;</hi> for thus he ſays of him, p. 38. <hi>And as to Counſellor</hi> Mallett, <hi>though he ſays</hi> that thee haſt dealt <hi>fairly by them, as in reſpect to Law, but did not, nor could not, as in reſpect to Tenderneſs and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</hi> Now the Reader may obſerve that theſe terms, <hi>viz. in reſpect to Law, to Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity,</hi> are not Counſellor <hi>Mallett</hi>'s words, but words thruſt in as his by <hi>Abraham Bonifield.</hi> Counſellor <hi>Mallett</hi> in the Judgment he gave, (and which I have before recited) did not ſay that I had dealt fairly by them as in reſpect to Law, (though <hi>A. B.</hi> hath the Impudence to Charge him with ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo) much leſs did he ſay, That he did not, nor could not, ſay I had dealt fairly with them, as in reſpect to Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity, (which <hi>A. B.</hi> falſly adds) but he uſed full and comprehenſive Terms, to expreſs his Judgment by, namely, <hi>That the ſaid</hi> O. S. <hi>hath in all the Tranſactions thereof, fully acquitted himſelf as a prudent and upright Perſon.</hi> In all the <hi>Tranſactions</hi> thereof. Doth that reſpect only Law? Or doth it not include <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> too? If I did (in Counſellor <hi>Mallett</hi>'s Judgment) fully acquit my ſelf as an upright Perſon in all the Tranſactions of that Buſineſs, with what Face, or Conſcience, could <hi>A. B.</hi> affirm as he does, That Counſellor <hi>Mallett</hi> did not, nor could not, ſay I had dealt fairly by them, as in reſpect of Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity? I do look upon Counſellor <hi>Mallett</hi> to have more Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity, than to think I could fully acquit my ſelf as a prudent and upright Perſon in all the Tranſactions of that Buſineſs, without Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may from hence know <hi>A. B.</hi> better than heretofore they have, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how they truſt themſelves to his Prudence and Uprightneſs, if it be void of Tenderneſs and Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I might further enlarge on this Subject from ſome paſſages in that Judgment given by Counſellor <hi>Mallett,</hi> and in his Letter to A. B. and there-from ſhew A. B. that he hath rendred himſelf (in the Counſellor's Judgment) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, and a Perſecutor.</hi> For in that Letter he expreſly calls thoſe Complaints, wherewith <hi>N. H.</hi> filled A. B's Ears againſt me, <hi>very unjuſt Complaints;</hi> what then but very unjuſt can A. B. be, in charging thoſe Complaints on me? And in his Judgment, the Counſellor ſays, <hi>I ought not be perſecuted ſo cauſleſly by the ſaid</hi> N. H. <hi>by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rumours to the contrary,</hi> (that is, as if I had not acted as an upright Perſon.) Now if this was Perſecution in <hi>N. H.</hi> how much a greater Perſecutor is A. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifield,</hi> who hath publiſhed theſe unjuſt Complaints againſt me in print, and that with his aggravating Obſervations on them, after he knew they had been judged <hi>unjuſt</hi> both by the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings, and afterwards by him to whom they were referred to be heard and ended? But I forbear enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and moſt willingly leave it to the Judgment of that Holy Witneſs and Judgment-ſeat which <hi>A. B.</hi> hath too <hi>preſumptuouſly</hi> appealed to, as he will find to his Sorrow one Day.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151315:25"/>
            <p>He inſinuates another Charge againſt me by way of Queſtion thus, <hi>And was it not alſo plainly proved againſt thee at a Meeting held at</hi> William Lambol<hi>'s the</hi> 26th <hi>of the</hi> 10th <hi>Month,</hi> 1694. <hi>and that before ſeveral of thy own Friends, and others alſo, that thee hadſt been both Remiſs in, and Falſe, and Treacherous alſo to thy Truſt, in the Caſe of</hi> Richard Daniell, <hi>late of</hi> Reading, <hi>in the which thee waſt concerned as an Executor with</hi> L. K. <hi>to the Will of the aforeſaid</hi> Daniell. To this I Anſwer, <hi>No,</hi> I believe that not one of my own Friends (as thou calls them) had any ſuch Thoughts in the leaſt, but were ſatisfied that I had acted uprightly both as a Man and a Chriſtian in that Affair; but I think I need ſay no more in this to <hi>A. B.</hi> but to put him in Remembrance (if he has willingly forgot it) how that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 14 Years ago, at a Monthly Meeting at <hi>Newberry</hi> I was charged with the ſame Matter, by ſome of thoſe Separatiſts to whom he is now gone (who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured then to hinder my Service in the Truth, and among Friends, and to have faſtened ſome Reproach or Defamation upon me by it; but they laboured in vain (as he now doth) for it was made appear to that Aſſembly, that I had been really Conſciencious and Sincere in all that I had acted and done in that Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. And that which is moſt Remarkable in it, with reſpect to <hi>A. B.</hi> is, that <hi>he was one that appeared on my Behalf, and for my Vindication in that Matter</hi> againſt him that Accuſed me.</p>
            <p>The next thing I intend to take notice of is in p. 40. where he ſays thus, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Widow</hi> Bunce <hi>of</hi> Gooſie (<hi>I mentioned,</hi> ſays A. B. <hi>in the general before,</hi> (but I do not find her ſo much as named before) <hi>in turning Juſtice and Equity backwards, and not allowing them to put it into Neighbours Hands to Judge the Truth.</hi> Theſe ſeems to be <hi>N. Hall</hi>'s words, that which follows is <hi>A. B</hi>'s Obſervations upon them, thus, <hi>Obſerve,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in a Matter of ſome Claim, Title, or Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet</hi> O. S. <hi>as you ſee must needs have a Finger in it too, as he uſed to do, as well as engage others with him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And therefore, as hinted, it appears they do, and will make themſelves Judges over Friends,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>both in Civil as well as Spiritual Things, and determine it; whereas her Honeſt Neighbours, as knew better of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Caſe, was wholly ſhut out from her Relief, to her great Injury,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And which her Son reſenting ſo very ill and unkindly, hath gone ſince to the Prieſt for a Wife,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe <hi>Et-cetera</hi>'s are A. B's own, no leſs than five in ſeven Lines; and I ſet them down as he has done, to ſhew what an idle infignificant Writer he is.</p>
            <p>But to proceed to anſwer to what he hath charged me with concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That a difference happening between the ſaid Widow <hi>Bunce</hi> and another Friend, and it being laid before the Monthly Meeting, the Meeting appointed ſome Friends to hear the Matter and endeavour to put an end to the ſaid Difference; of them that were ſo appointed by the Meeting, I was one, and no otherwiſe was I concerned or had (to uſe A. <hi>B</hi>'s Phraſe) a Finger in it, but to help with others to make it up. And through the Bleſſing of God, our endeavours therein proved Succeſsful. The Breach was made up, and Friends were ſatisfied concerning it. But what (if one may be ſo bold as to ask) had A. B. to do to put his Finger into it, now ſo long after it hath been made up? Or what other End or Deſign can he be ſuppoſed to have therein, but either to rip up, and tear open the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151315:25"/>again, and make a new Breach upon it, if he could, (which is the Work of the Wicked One) by ſuggeſting, as if Juſtice and Equity had been turned backwards, and the Woman greatly Injured, becauſe (both the Parties being Friends) the Matter was undertaken by Friends, and not left to her Honeſt Neighbours (the Worlds People, as it ſeems A. B. in ſuch Caſes would have) or elſe, that he deſigns by thus Miſrepreſenting the Matter, to throw ſome more of his Dirt at me, as if I had thruſt my Finger into this Buſineſs, as he has done his, without being duly called to it, and had thereby occaſioned the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to ſuſt in great Injury. But that the Widow <hi>Bunce</hi> her ſelf had no ſuch apprehenſion concerning me, nor the leaſt diſtruſt of my juſt and fair dealing with her in that buſineſs, may well, I think, be gathered from this. That after that matter was ended, and over, when ſhe was to go into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to live with her Daughter there, ſhe hath entruſted me (as much or more) than any Friend or Relation ſhe hath in <hi>England,</hi> to Receive her Rents here, and to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them over to her in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In p. 41. he taxes me with <hi>Serving him a baſe unworthy falſe deceitful trick, nigh or full half a ſcore years ago, about the things that he was to buy for the Friends that were Priſoners in</hi> Newgate, <hi>and which for the better accomodating of them, he did</hi> (he ſays) <hi>in reality, and without reſerve, deſire my aſſiſtance to him in it, in order to do them the greater kindneſs; yet nevertheleſs I</hi> (he ſays) <hi>for my own Ends and Intereſt, acted quite contrary to the ſaid end propoſed by him, as well as to the Friends diſadvantage, that were not in a condition to ſo well help themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. This is an high Charge ſet forth in <hi>foul</hi> and aggravating terms. He calls it a baſe, unworthy, falſe, deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful trick; <hi>His words are not as ſmooth as Oyl,</hi> which he ſays mine are, p. 33. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it his manner to relate things plainly and fairly; why did he not open what this (which he calls a trick) was, that the Reader might underſtand, and be able to judge whether it was (as he calls it) <hi>baſe, unworthy, falſe, and deceitful.</hi> He ſays <hi>I acted quite contrary to the end propoſed by him,</hi> and that I did this <hi>for my owns Ends and Intereſt, as well as to the Friends diſadvantage.</hi> The End he ſays <hi>he propoſed, was to buy things for the Friends that were Priſoners, for the better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modating of them.</hi> Now from his ſaying that I acted quite contrary to the ſaid end propoſed by him; one that knows nothing either of the buſineſs, or of me, might ſuſpect, either that I had bought nothing at all for them, but <hi>bad run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with their Money:</hi> Or elſe, that if I did buy things for them, <hi>I cheated them in the buying of it,</hi> and made an <hi>advantage to my ſelf</hi> thereby. And 'tis likely that A. <hi>B.</hi> delivered this matter ſo darkly, on purpoſe to <hi>miſlead</hi> his Reader into ſome ſuch ill apprehenſion of me. But if that was his deſign, I do hope to defeat it, by giving the Reader a true and plain account of the matter, ſo far as I can remember, to the beſt of my knowledge, which is thus; A. <hi>B.</hi> it ſeems was imployed to buy certain Goods for ſome Friends that were Priſoners in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> for them to ſell again by retail; and he thinking (I ſuppoſe) that I had more Knowledge therein than himſelf, deſired me to buy them (I being at that time a Priſoner my ſelf in <hi>Reading,</hi> but having ſome liberty to walk in the Town) accordingly I did buy the Goods as carefully and faithfully as I could; but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſeems was my overſight, and that which gave ſo great an offence, namely,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151315:26"/>that I did not buy thoſe Goods of that Perſon whom A. <hi>B.</hi> hath ſince ſaid he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended I ſhould, but had them of another; but whether this was my miſtake in receiving my Errand or A. <hi>B</hi>'s in giving it me, I know not. However I know of no wrong or diſadvantage that came to the Priſoners thereby, nor of any gain or advantage that did accrue to me by it. Therefore in his ſaying I did it for my own Ends and Intereſt, as well as to the diſadvantage of the Friends the Priſoners, he hath therein ſpoken a double untruth, and as for his railing and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter language expreſſed towards the cloſe of that Paragraph, let the Lord rebuke him.</p>
            <p>He ſhoots another of his Bolts at me in p. 42. about my Brother's Widow, which he brings in thus, <hi>And again as to his Treachery, Hard-heartedneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>what need I ſo trouble my ſelf, or have fetcht ſuch a circuit round to prove this Man,</hi> O. S: <hi>Treacherous, Hard-hearted, and without Natural affection to others, when ſeen, found, and known to be ſo at home, as I may ſay even to his own Relations, as witneſs his hardy, ſower, and moroſs carriage towards his own Brother's Wife.</hi> In this as well as in the reſt, he runs himſelf aground, and bewrays his own Folly. He charges me with <hi>Treachery and Hard-heartedneſs</hi> toward my Brother's Widow, and for Proof thereof alledges that my carriage towards her was <hi>hardy, ſower and moroſs;</hi> now if this were as true as it is falſe, yet doth hardy, ſower, moroſs carriage prove a Man to be Treacherous? O then <hi>moſt Treacherous</hi> A. <hi>Bonifield,</hi> for who more ſower and moroſs than he, as this his Book ſhews? But if that be not a proof of Treachery (which none but ſuch a Wiſe Man as himſelf, will ſay it is) his bringing it here for a proof thereof, is a ſufficient proof his own Envy and Folly.</p>
            <p>But as to my Brother's Widow, and my carriage towards her, I can truly ſay, I had a compaſſionate love to her, and did from my Heart wiſh her well every way. And I do not know that my carriage towards her, was either hardy, ſower, or moroſs, or other than became the Profeſſion of Truth, and the Relation that was between us. Yet I had cauſe ſometimes to ſpeak plain, and that which it is poſſible might not be pleaſing to her, but ſhe well knew that my end therein, was only and alone, on behalf of my ſaid Brother's Children, which he had by a former Wife, the Care of whom lay ſomewhat upon me, not only as a near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but by my Father's Will appointed an Overſeer, to ſee and endeavour that they might not be deprived of certain Legacies which in and by the ſaid Will was bequeathed to them, which if I had not endeavoured, A. <hi>B.</hi> might then have charged me, and that truly, with (what he now doth falſly) Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</p>
            <p>I have now gone through his Book, ſo as to anſwer whatſoever ſeemed to have any appearance of weight in it, and I hope to the Reader's ſatisfaction. But for his confuſed Clamours with which his Book abounds, eſpecially the latter part of it, vented in a Stile of <hi>Billingsgate</hi> Rhetorick, I do not think it worth my while to trouble my ſelf or my Reader any further about it; but I ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn a Teſtimony from the Friends of the Monthly Mens Meeting of <hi>Farringdon</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and there-a-ways, which of it ſelf might, I ſuppoſe, have been ſufficient to have clear'd my Reputation in the Judgment of the Impartial, from the Muck
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151315:26"/>and Dirt which in his Book he has endeavoured to caſt upon it, and then come to a Concluſion.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The ſaid Teſtimony is as followeth.</head>
                  <p>WHereas there is a Book lately Publiſhed by <hi>Abraham Bonifield,</hi> Entituled. <hi>The Cry of the Oppreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. tending to the diſhonour of the Name of the Lord, and to the defaming of many Ancient Friends, who have long been known and approved by their faithful Teſtimony and Sufferings for the Truth; and alſo by their diligent Exerciſe in ſerving the Church of Chriſt. And more particularly our dear Friend <hi>Oliver Sanſom,</hi> (who is a Member of this Meeting) is greatly wronged and abuſed by the ſaid A. <hi>B.</hi> in his foreſaid Book, which in two remarkable Matters, that have been fully and fairly heard and determined in our Monthly Meetings (<hi>viz.</hi> the buſineſs of <hi>N. Hall</hi> and his Wife, and that of the Widow <hi>Bunce</hi>) we do hereby declare, that within our own Knowledge, the Accuſations which A. <hi>B.</hi> from thence would faſten upon <hi>O. S.</hi> are utterly falſe. And we being Witneſſes of his Chriſtian Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on all accounts among us all along, are alſo fully ſatisfied, that all his other Allegations againſt the aforeſaid, are alſo falſe, which by the Spirit of Envy in A. <hi>B.</hi> are forged and brought forth for no other end, but to bring him, the ſaid <hi>O. S.</hi> undeſervedly into contempt. Wherefore we do look upon our ſelves concerned for the Honour of the Holy Truth, and for the Reputation of him and other our dear Friends and Brethren (who have been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning both diligent, faithful and conſtant in the Work and Service of the Lord) to give forth this our Teſtimony againſt the injurious attempts of this Envious Apoſtate Adverſary.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given forth at a Monthly Mens Meeting held at</hi> Weſt Chawlow <hi>in the</hi> Vale <hi>of</hi> White-Horſe, <hi>in the County of</hi> Berks,
<date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 27th <hi>of the</hi> 12th <hi>Month,</hi> 1695.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>And by Appointment and on Behalf of the ſaid Meeting: Signed by
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Vokins,</hi> Sen.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Daniel Bunce,</hi> Sen.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edw. Lockey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Adam Lawrence,</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After he had brought his Book to an end, and had ſet to it <hi>The End,</hi> he hath added four pages more (ſhewing himſelf to be confuſed and whimſical in the manner, as well as in the matter of it) and that he calls a ſhort Addition (having a Poſtſcript before) and in that which he calls a ſhort Addition p. 45. He ſays thus, <hi>Neither this, nor any other Difference of any Nature or Kind whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is or can in Truth be ſaid to be ended, until the Reconciliation be wrought, and Peace made between the Parties that differed; and this he ſays, one would think is ſo plain and clear, that no Capacity, tho' never ſo weak or ſmall, but muſt needs diſcern, believe and ſee it.</hi> If his Capacity had not been of the ſmalleſt ſize, he might have diſcerned, what a foundation he has here laid, ſhould it be allowed, to perpetuate Differences, and render them impoſſible ever to be ended, for it is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151315:27"/>too frequently ſeen in ſuch caſes, that one or both of the differing Parties do obſtinately refuſe to be reconciled: But towards the lower end of the ſame page, he grants at length, thus, <hi>That if the Parties or Referrees to whom the matter in difference is referred, be in good earnest, and do uſe their utmoſt endeavours for Peace and Reconciliation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet if any one of the Perſons or Parties concerned, do ſtand out and be refractory, and refuſe to yield compliance to the Judgment of the aforeſaid, all the rest are clear and to be excuſed, and the blame wholly and alone to be placed upon the obſtinate, or refuſing Perſon or Party,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in caſe that Partiality and Injuſtice be not the cauſe of his overſeneſs.</hi> This I like well, and am ſo fully aſſured, that we (whom he unjuſtly calls the ſeven unjuſt Judges) to whom the matters in Difference between <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and himſelf were referred, were in <hi>very good earneſt,</hi> and did uſe our <hi>utmoſt endeavours</hi> for Peace and Reconciliation (in Truth) and that tho' A. <hi>B.</hi> do ſtand out, was refractory, and did refuſe to yield compliance to the Judgment given by us, yet there was <hi>no Partiality</hi> or <hi>Injuſtice</hi> on our parts, which might be the cauſe of his <hi>averſeneſs.</hi> That with great Satisfaction and Content of Mind, I can, and do leave and ſubmit it to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God's Holy Witneſs in the Hearts of his People here, and to the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt hereafter.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing it is ſo plainly proved, by poſitive Evidence, and moſt clear Demonſtration, (which cannot be denied) that A. <hi>B.</hi> is deeply guilty of doing great wrong to me and others, therefore God's Holy Witneſt in the Hearts of his People (which is juſt and true) muſt needs judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him for it: Now this is what I (in true love to his Soul) do ſincerely deſire, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of his ſad Eſtate, and wait in Humility upon the Lord, to know ſuch <hi>a Godly ſorrow that may work in him a true Repentance unto Life Eternal:</hi> For if this be not witneſſed by him while he have time, with what confidence can he think to appear before that <hi>Dreadful Tribunal</hi> or <hi>Judgment-Seat,</hi> which he (in an haughty mind to make a vain flouriſh) hath preſumed to Appeal unto, where he muſt certainly <hi>be Rewarded</hi> according to his doings.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Abingdon <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 29th <hi>of the</hi> 1ſt <hi>Month,</hi> 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>O. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is one thing more which may not be improper to be taken notice of, though I had once thought to have paſſed it over with a ſlight hint in p.</hi> 42. <hi>but upon a ſecond conſideration, concluded it might be of ſome Service (tho' it be but a ſmall matter, and there are ſo many greater matters to be found fault with in his Book) to ſhew that</hi> A. B <hi>is as fooliſh as conceited. I did intend to have inſerted this in p.</hi> 42. <hi>where it is ſomething touched upon before; but I being in the Country, it came too late to the Printer's Hand, and therefore it is added by way of</hi> Poſtſcript. <hi>'Tis his</hi> Etcetera's <hi>which (having leiſure) I did for curioſity caſt up, where I found ſuch an unuſual plenty of them in his Book, that there are fifteen of them in ſome ſingle pages, and near three hundred of them in the whole Book, though it be not eight, ſheets of Print; ſome whereof are very inſignificant and impertinently added: As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, p.</hi> 40. <hi>ſpeaking concerning the Widow</hi> Bunce<hi>'s Son, he ſays,</hi> He went to the Prieſt for a Wiſe, <hi>&amp;c. What would he have his Reader think he went for beſides a Wife? For his</hi> Etcetera <hi>implies ſomething more than a Wife. Again, in p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 45. <hi>he ſays,</hi> he with the reſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did: <hi>Which is as proper as if he had ſaid</hi> he with the reſt and the reſt did. <hi>So p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 4. Meeting with him at <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious-ſtreet</hi> Meeting at the time of the Yearly Meeting, <hi>&amp;c. So p.</hi> 18. There ended the matter as the full and reſult of all and the whole, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (viz. <hi>the reſt beſides the whole) ſee alſo</hi> Epiſt. p. 9. <hi>again in p</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 14.15. Any Nation, Country, Kingdom or Place whatſoever throughout the whole World, <hi>&amp;c. Nay ſo filly is he as to put in, or cauſe to put in with a Pen theſe uſeleſs</hi> Etceteras <hi>in divers places where the Printer had the Diſcretion to leave them out, as in the page laſt cited and ſome others.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 19. for <hi>the Capital</hi> read <hi>that Capital,</hi> p. 13. l. 31. for <hi>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> r. <hi>the,</hi> p. 16. l. 24. for 10th. r. 5th, p. 18. l. 23. for <hi>Meteting</hi> r. <hi>Meeting,</hi> l. 24. for <hi>theſe</hi> r. <hi>thoſe,</hi> p. 20. l. 2. r. <hi>but that he,</hi> l. 29. for 36. r. 37. p. 21. l. 15. for <hi>the Quarterly</hi> r. <hi>that Quarterly,</hi> l. 16. r. <hi>laſt Quarterly,</hi> l. 19. dele <hi>ſame,</hi> l. 21. for <hi>matters</hi> r. <hi>matter,</hi> l. 34. for <hi>mateer</hi> r. <hi>matter,</hi> l. 35. for <hi>the r. that,</hi> p. 22. l. 2. for <hi>away, and,</hi> r. <hi>away, &amp;c.</hi> p. 28. l. 8. for <hi>A.</hi> B. r. <hi>J.</hi> B. l. 39. for <hi>had</hi> r. <hi>hath,</hi> p. 31. l. 8. for <hi>weeks</hi> r. <hi>years,</hi> Ibid. r. <hi>enquiry made,</hi> l. 10. for <hi>the charge</hi> r. <hi>this charge,</hi> p. 35. l. 12. for <hi>or</hi> r. <hi>for.</hi> p. 44. l. 23. r. <hi>of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151315:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
